<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Featlæi paliggenesia or, Doctor Daniel Featley revived: proving, that the Protestant church (and not the Romish) is the onely Catholick and true church. In a manual preserved from the hands of the plunderers. With a succinct history of his life and death. / Published by John Featley, chaplain to the Kings most Excellent Majesty.</title>
            <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 109 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85179</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868937</idno>
  <idno type="VID">121294</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240947036</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1937_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R210110</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868937</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99868937e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85179)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 121294)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 240:E1937[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Featlæi paliggenesia or, Doctor Daniel Featley revived: proving, that the Protestant church (and not the Romish) is the onely Catholick and true church. In a manual preserved from the hands of the plunderers. With a succinct history of his life and death. / Published by John Featley, chaplain to the Kings most Excellent Majesty.</title>
                  <author>Featley, John, 1605?-1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 114, [2], 86, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nath. Brook, at the Angel in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"A succinct history of the life and death of the learned and famous divine, Daniel Featly Doctor in Divinity" has separate dated title page; with separate pagination, register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>The second word in the title is in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>With final advertisements leaf.</note>
                  <note>Errata leaf follows text.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "xber [i.e. December] 20."; "Decem".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Featley, Daniel, 1582-1645 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:121294:1"/>
            <p>Featlaei <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: OR, Doctor <hi>Daniel Featley</hi> REVIVED: Proving, <hi>That the Protestant Church</hi> (and not the <hi>Romish</hi>) <hi>is the onely Catholick and true Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a MANUAL preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the hands of the Plunderers.</p>
            <p>With a Succinct HISTORY OF HIS Life and Death.</p>
            <p>Published by <hi>John Featley,</hi> Chaplain to the Kings most Excellent Majesty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Brook,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:121294:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE Sacred Majesty OF Our Royal Sovereign, CHARLES II. By Divine Providence King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it please your Majesty,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>SUbjects without their Sovereign are but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; a <hi>Headless</hi> Trunk; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a <hi>heedless</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. This hath been for
<pb facs="tcp:121294:3"/>many years (ah, too many!) the <hi>Mayme</hi> and <hi>Malady</hi> of these Your Majesties distra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Kingdomes; wherein through the Rage and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Faction,
<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 12.21.</note> the <hi>hand</hi> said unto the <hi>eye</hi> (if I may invert the words of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle,) and the <hi>feet</hi> unto the <hi>head, we have no need of you:</hi> yea,
<note n="b" place="margin">Ver. 23.</note> and those members of the body which we <hi>know</hi> to be less honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, on them <hi>the Errours of the times</hi> bestowed more abundant honor.</p>
                  <p>But it becometh not me to be one of <hi>Solomon's
<note n="c" place="margin">Prov. 20 3.</note> med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dlers;</hi> or <hi>infandum renovare dolorem.</hi> Our long and sad Laments are now (even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove hope) drowned in our Joys; and our <hi>Groanes</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:121294:3"/>
                     <hi>Cryes</hi> are converted into <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sanna's</hi> to that All-mighty <hi>King of Kings,</hi> who alone hath (even to the extasie of our Admiration) both pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served Your sacred Person; and restored You to Your People. This year is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore most truly ANNUS LIBERTATIS AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GLIAE; <hi>The Year of</hi> your Subjects safest <hi>Liberty:</hi> For
<q>
                        <l>—<note n="d" place="margin">Anson.</note> Nunquam-libertas gratior extat,</l>
                        <l>Quam sub rege pio. —</l>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 12.3.</note> The <hi>contradiction of sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners,</hi> and the Romane FU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GALIA, are turned into <hi>Acclamations</hi> of Christian <hi>Loyalty,</hi> and <hi>the Voice of Gladness.</hi> We, alas, <hi>slept</hi> out too many years in a dark and stupid <hi>Lethargy:</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:121294:4"/>yet <hi>now</hi> also, even in this unexpected
<note n="f" place="margin">Psalm 126.1.</note> turning of our Captivity, we are but like unto them that <hi>dream.</hi> The Lord <hi>awake</hi> us into a quick sense of our great Deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; that the Glory may be <hi>his,</hi> and <hi>his</hi> onely,
<note n="g" place="margin">Psalm 136.4.</note> who alone doth great wonders; who alone doth
<note n="h" place="margin">Psal. 65.7.</note> still the noise of the <hi>Seas,</hi> the noise of their <hi>waves,</hi> and <hi>the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult of the people.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Every Loyal Subject some way or other testifieth his joy for the Miracle of Your Majesties Return: and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny express it by their <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will Offerings.</hi> I am there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unwilling to appeare <hi>empty;</hi> although this little <hi>Honorary</hi> may be unworthy Your Majesties reception.
<pb facs="tcp:121294:4"/>The Author thereof (my dearest Uncle) intended it for Your Royal <hi>Father;</hi> to whom both <hi>he,</hi> and <hi>mine</hi> unworthy <hi>self,</hi> were most obliged servants: but being denied that honour by the churlishness of the Times, he committed it to <hi>my</hi> trust, even at a time when (to preserve mine <hi>Allegiance</hi>) I was compelled to <hi>flie upon the wings of the winde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But,
<q>Diffugere nives, redeunt jam gramina campis.</q> That <hi>Storm</hi> is turned into a <hi>Calm:</hi> Now therefore, even by the Command of Christ, QUAE CAESARIS CAESARI. This Book is due to Your Majesty,
<pb facs="tcp:121294:5"/>both as you are the just and undoubted Heir of Your Glorious Father; and as to me a most gracious Master. <hi>Little</hi> it is; but the <hi>Iliades</hi> in a <hi>Nut-shell</hi> found accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance. The subject matter (I suppose) is not unseasonable; it being Your Majesties pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Design to restore <hi>the true Reformed Protestant Church</hi> in these Your Dominions to her <hi>Purity,</hi> and pristine <hi>Glory:</hi> in the <hi>prosession</hi> of whose most holy <hi>Faith</hi> you have been so wonderfully <hi>preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You, GREAT SIR, are not onely <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> but also
<note n="i" place="margin">Isa. 49.23.</note>
                     <hi>Nutritius Ecclesia;</hi> under the shadow of whose wings she findes protection. For even the <hi>Church</hi> it self is
<pb facs="tcp:121294:5"/>enforced to take <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> to shun the subtilty and rage of
<note n="k" place="margin">Nehem. 2 19.</note>
                     <hi>Sanballat</hi> and <hi>Tobiah;</hi> the <hi>Papists</hi> on the one side; and the <hi>Sectaries</hi> and <hi>Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> on the other. That hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>grace,</hi> and Princely <hi>pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> and <hi>prudence</hi> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centre in Your Majesty; to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with Your Royal and Just Title of DEFEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER OF THE FAITH; assure us that you will ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly cherish this
<note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 2.2</note>
                     <hi>Lilie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the thorns;</hi> and (if not retarded by our <hi>impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>) <hi>hasten</hi> her <hi>Restaura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Sad, I confess, is the present condition of our <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> the <hi>Church; Jacob</hi> and <hi>Esaeu</hi> strugling in her womb: yet not the rash <hi>violence,</hi> but the <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>skill</hi> of her
<pb facs="tcp:121294:6"/>
                     <hi>Midwife</hi> must help to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver her. The tender issue of our younger Brother <hi>Benja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min</hi> (who <hi>think</hi> they can
<note n="m" place="margin">Judges 20.16</note> sling stones with their <hi>left hands</hi> at an haires breadth) might more highly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage (as I humbly conceive) the Work of Christ, if they would be more forward to approve of what the <hi>right hand</hi> doth. Certainly a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate <hi>Complyance,</hi> and a dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet <hi>Condescension</hi> in things <hi>indifferent,</hi> even on both sides, will best savour of that Heavenly <hi>Wisdom,</hi> which is first pure, then peaceable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It was the <hi>Dove,</hi> not the <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> which brought the <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live-leaf</hi> into <hi>Noahs Ark.</hi> That famous Speech of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bram</hi> to <hi>Lot</hi> is still canonical,
<pb facs="tcp:121294:6"/>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 13.8.</note>
                     <hi>Let there be no strife, I pray thee, between me and thee, and between my herdmen and thy herdmen; for we are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> I suppose that the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimate and faithful <hi>sons</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> (remembring how lately they <hi>really suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> what the
<note n="o" place="margin">Josh 9.4, 5</note> Gibeonitish Embassadors did but <hi>counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit</hi>) will now rather
<note n="p" place="margin">Ezra 3.12, 13.</note>
                     <hi>shout</hi> for <hi>joy</hi> that Your Majesty bath laid again the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the house of the Lord; then <hi>weep</hi> in remembrance of the former glory. A tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Reformation (not hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>critically pretended as of late, but really effected) will be a Work of <hi>time:</hi> and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less that God who hath brought to the <hi>birth,</hi> will in his owne <hi>due time</hi> give
<pb facs="tcp:121294:7"/>strength to <hi>bring forth. Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken joynts</hi> may soon be well <hi>set;</hi> but the members must be content to recover <hi>strength</hi> by degrees. The Lord in mercy preserve your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty; and make You a Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Lasting Instrument to <hi>repair</hi> all our <hi>breaches;</hi> and to <hi>build again the old waste places</hi> of his <hi>Church</hi> amongst us. Thus prayeth</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Majesties loyal Subject, and most faithful servant,</hi> John Featley.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121294:7"/>
                  <head>CERTAIN DOUBTS OF <hi>S. B.</hi> Resolved by Dr. <hi>Dan. Featly,</hi> against Popery, asserting the Protestants Church to be the onely Catholick and true Church.</head>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Dr.</hi> Featley's <hi>Provise touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Protestants Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <q>I Perswade my self, that <hi>S. B.</hi> makes not these men in each age cited, the onely Professors of the true Church; but that then the Roman Church was a true one, though sick and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seased; and that these men
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121294:8"/>and they were members of the same one Catholick Church; also, these stout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly oppose those odde in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions which the prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and more populous side pinned and annexed to the Unity of Faith.</q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>The Answer of</hi> Dr. <hi>D. F.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>SIr, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> it grieves me much to see Men of War of the same Fleet, and sailing under the fame Admiral, and with the same commission to fight against Antichrist, <hi>fall foul</hi> one of the other; although they have <hi>Sea room enough,</hi> and might safely hold on in their own course, and one need not crosse the others hawser; for <hi>Ithacus velit &amp;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121294:8"/>magno mercentur Achivi:</hi> This sole consideration with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held me from interposing my judgement in the late unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py differences between the Champions of the Gospel, concerning the present state of the Roman Church: though I was required so to do by a worthy and reverend Prelate of this Kingdom. Yet because I know you love the truth in sincerity, and propose that among your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doubts, not any way to entangle me, but expedite your self, or satisfie some of your friends: I will return a punctual answer to the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure of your book:</p>
                     <p>And first, Whereas the reverend and learned Prelate would have your book read
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121294:9"/>with this Proviso,
<q>That you make not those men in every age cited by you, to be the onely Professors of the true Church:</q> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that caution to be need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less: for neither do you as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to your self, neither did the Adversary put the task upon you, to cite <hi>all</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors of the true Religion in all ages; (which had been <hi>opus Iliae majus</hi>) but to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce some eminent witnesses in each age; which you have done faithfully, and thereby procur'd you as many friends as you have alleaded testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies. What the Orator spake of the <hi>State,</hi> is true in the <hi>Church,</hi> the Church hath a large field: many may run their races in it, &amp; be crown'd
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121294:9"/>with honor.
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cic. Phil.</hi> 4.</note>
                        <hi>Magnus est in Ecclesia campus, multis patet apertus cursus ad laudem.</hi> You have run well, and out-stript many: it may be some here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after may outstrip you: I know you will account that no loss, because it will be the truths gain. The <hi>Evidence</hi> which you take out of good Records, and well sorted ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to every <hi>age,</hi> is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to convince the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish adversary: and fairer and clearer in any one Writter I have not seen. Yet I must confess, that our cause doth not depend onely upon those evidences: Neither doe I think any Protestant in the world, will undertake to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all Records and Testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies which may be found
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121294:10"/>for the truth of our Religion in all Antiquity.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> whereas he add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,
<q>That even then the Roman Church was a true Church, though sick and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seased; and that these men and they were members of the same true Catholick Church:</q> I apprehend not sufficiently either the truth of his assertion, or the since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his intention. For what have we to do with the Roman Church? I blush, that any Protestant should open his mouth for that <hi>Whore of</hi> Babylon, <hi>who hath dyed her garments scarlet red in the blood of the Noble fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runners of our faith:
<note place="margin">
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>udg. 6.3.</note> If</hi> Baal <hi>be a god, let him plead for himself;</hi> if the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi>
                        <pb n="7" facs="tcp:121294:10"/>hath any right, either to the Catholick Church, or any true &amp; visible member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; let him plead his title by himself, or his <hi>learned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil.</hi> We are <hi>retained by the adverse part</hi> against him; but his intention and others, who of late times have set on foot this title of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I leave to the searcher of all hearts. As for our as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion, I will make bold to demur upon it; and the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, because Protestants and Papists at this time stand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the same tearms as <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Autonie</hi> did after <hi>Julius Caesars</hi> death:
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cie. Phit.</hi> 4.</note>
                        <hi>Si consul An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius, Brutus hostis: si con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servator reipub. Brutus, hostis Autonius:</hi> If the Roman Church be the true Church,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121294:11"/>the Reformed Churches, which are condemned, and excommunicated, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted to death by her, must needs be false Churches: If Papists are <hi>Catholicks</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the word, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants, which are the <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brum contradivisum,</hi> the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posite number, must needs be Hereticks. And this the late Archbishop of <hi>Canterbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and the rest of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Commissioners, made a clear case in the censure of the Lady <hi>Wotton,</hi> who was fined 500 <hi>l.</hi> for an inscription on the Monument of her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, dying a Recusant, <hi>Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrissim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>, &amp;c. D.</hi> Wottono <hi>Catholico, ego catholica hoc posui:</hi> To the most renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121294:11"/>
                        <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Lord <hi>Wotton,</hi> a Catholick; I, his Widow, a Catholick also, have erected this Monument.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Catholique,</hi> if we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to the Greek Etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie, fignifieth nothing but <hi>General</hi> and <hi>Universal;</hi> and according to the subject to which it is applied, is either taken in the good sense, or in the ill. For as we read in the Physicians of <hi>Catholick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies,</hi> such as are good a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all, or the greater part of diseases: so they tell us also of <hi>Catholique,</hi> or epide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical <hi>Diseases,</hi> such as run through whole Countreys: And in such a sense, I will not eagerly contest with the Romanists, but that <hi>Popery</hi> may be called <hi>Catholick;</hi>
                        <pb n="10" facs="tcp:121294:12"/>because it cannot be denied, but that the greatest part of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> are infected with this disease.</p>
                     <p>As for the sense of the word, as it is attributed to the <hi>Church,</hi> it is double: 1. Either it signifieth <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal,</hi> or <hi>Oecumenical:</hi> and so it is taken in the Creed, and is opposed to the Synagogue of the Jews which was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to a certain time, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, and places: whereas the <hi>Catholick</hi> Christian Church, is absolutely illimitted, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting into it believers of all sorts, in all places, at all times. 2. Or it signifieth <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxal,</hi> in all points needful to salvation: and fo it is taken for the most part in the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of ancient Fathers: by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121294:12"/>name by Saint <hi>Cyril,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>c.</hi> 8. <hi>cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mystag.</hi>
                        </note> who adviseth, <hi>When thou co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest into any City to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, Where is the Catholick Church? for that is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per name of the Holy Church, which is the Mother of us all: and she is so termed, because she catholickly and perfectly teacheth all Doctrines which men are bound to know,</hi> &amp;c. and <hi>Paciamus,
<note place="margin">Ep. ad Spin Pron.</note> Christian is my name, and Catholick my sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name: by the one I am known from Infidels, by the other from Hereticks and Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks.</hi> And by S. <hi>Austine, Although every heresie would seem to be,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>L. Con Ep. fund. c</hi> 4. <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>exet po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stremo &amp; ipsum Catholicae nemen, quod non sine causa inter tam multas baereses ista fola Ecclesia hoo nomen obti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuit</hi>
                           </note> and affecteth to be called the Catholick Church: yet when Hereticks are asked
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121294:13"/>of Pagans, Where is the place in which Catholickes meet? none of them dares point to his own house or church.</hi> And again, <hi>The very Title of the Catholick Church holdeth me, which name among so many heresies she alone retaineth.</hi> And by <hi>Theodosius</hi> the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peror,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sozomen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> 7 <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odosius de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crevit, ut illorum ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxat Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceretur, quae Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quali hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re coleret.</hi>
                        </note>
                        <hi>who made a decree that the Church of them should a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone be called Catholick, which equally worshipped and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the three persons in the blessed Trinity.</hi> In neither of these senses can the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> without either ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surdity or impiety, be termed <hi>Catholick.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Not in the first sense: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> for the Roman Church is no more the <hi>Universal</hi> Church, then <hi>Rome,</hi> or the Roman Jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121294:13"/>is the whole world. This Grand imposture is so discovered by the Bishop of <hi>Durham,</hi> that I suppose, as the Roman South-sayers could not look one upon the other without smiling, so neither can any Papist tearm another <hi>Catholick</hi> in this sense, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out laughing in his sleeve. <hi>Pacianus</hi> saith pertinently, <hi>That the name</hi> Catholick <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the stock of the Tree, which remaineth the same;</hi> &amp; est quid totum, <hi>and is a kinde of whole and entire thing.</hi> The Roman Church at the best is but a great Branch, and such a one as we can prove is much withered; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom</hi> 11.21, 22.</note>
                        <hi>may be cut off: If God spared not the natural branches, take heed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121294:14"/>lest he spare not thee. Behold therefore the goodness and severity of God: on them which fell, severity; but to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee goodness, if thou continue in his goodness; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise thou shalt bee cut off.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Much less in the second sense can the church of <hi>Rome</hi> be tearmed <hi>Catholick:</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> for whereas other hereticks were so termed, because they held but some <hi>one</hi> error or other against the <hi>Catholick</hi> Faith: the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth <hi>many,</hi> and those most grievous and pernicious: as in the Articles, Homilies, and Apology of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and in the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of all Prorestants Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessions, is ocularly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strated.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121294:14"/>If any Protestant therefore tearm the Roman Church <hi>Catholick,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Whitaker <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Eccles con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> 2 <hi>q</hi> 5 <hi>Nos illos non atiter vocamus Catholicos, quam illi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>os refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>tos &amp; Eva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>geli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                                 <desc>•••</desc>
                              </gap>▪ hoc est <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>ronice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>ntum &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>on ex ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</hi>
                        </note> it is but by an Ironie, or bitter Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casm: like to that of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians,</hi> whereby they styled <hi>Alexander</hi> a God; <hi>Quia Alexander vult esse Deus, sit Deus:</hi> Because <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> will be a God, let him be a God. Or that of St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> whereby he sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth certain hereticks <hi>Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>In Cant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>er</hi> 66. <hi>
                                 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                                    <desc>••</desc>
                                 </gap>
                                 <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctant se esse Apostolo rum suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessores &amp; Apostolte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>s nominant: nullum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctolatus sui signum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stendere.</hi>
                           </note> because they arrogantly challenged to themselves that title: These,</hi> forsooth, <hi>call themselves</hi> Apostolicks, <hi>and yet they are not able to shew any sign or token of their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postleship:</hi> so may we say, and most truly, Papists call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves <hi>Catholicks;</hi> yet cannot shew any note or true mark
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121294:15"/>of a <hi>Catholick</hi> in them.</p>
                     <p>Thus much for the first At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute, <hi>Catholick:</hi> the next to which he Entituleth the Roman Church, <hi>viz. True,</hi> is either ambiguous and frivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, or false and scandalous.</p>
                     <p>For first, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> if he speak of Metaphysical Truth (which is of as large extent as <hi>entity,</hi> or being) his Assertion, That the Roman Church is a <hi>True Church</hi> (that is no phantasm or chymaera) is, as the French use to speak, <hi>an extream ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> a thing so evident and notorious, that no wise man would contend for it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause no fool ever called it in question. Who knoweth not what we finde in <hi>Tertullian, that Wasps have their hives, as well as Bees?</hi> and that <hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks</hi>
                        <pb n="17" facs="tcp:121294:15"/>have had their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations no less visible (nay sometimes more visible) then <hi>Catholtcks?</hi> Nay, not onely Hereticks, but Jews, Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metans, and Heathen Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, have had for many ages multitudes of professours of their Impieties and Supersti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: and not onely <hi>visible,</hi> but <hi>celebrious</hi> and solemn Assemblies, in most parts of the Christian world. <hi>Truth of existence</hi> they have all, but <hi>existence of truth</hi> (especially all saving truth) they have not. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> If by <hi>truth</hi> he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stand <hi>Logical,</hi> or rather <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical truth,</hi> opposed to Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Heresies in matters of Faith. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> Then he must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily revoke his subscrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the Articles of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121294:16"/>Church of <hi>England,</hi> which charge the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> by name,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Art.</hi> 19</note> with <hi>blasphemous figments, pernicious impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stures, and dangerous errours even in matter of faith.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He must condemn the apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the church of <hi>England,</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> wherein it is alledged for our separation from <hi>Rome,
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Apoli y Church of</hi> England <hi>c</hi> 16 <hi>divis</hi> 1. <hi>part</hi> 6.</note> that regard of our own salvation constrained us so to do: and that we are fallen from the Bishop of</hi> Rome,
<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Part</hi> 6. <hi>divis.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 20.</note>
                        <hi>because the case stood so, that unless we left him, we could not come to Christ:
<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Part</hi> 5. <hi>cap</hi> 15. <hi>divis</hi> 3.</note> and that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced that Church wherein there was nothing able to stay a wise man, or one that hath consideration of his own safety</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> he must take to task all <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121294:16"/>that have lifted up their spears against the Romane Antichrist,
<note place="margin">Whitaker Succliff <hi>Tract. dc Eccles.</hi> Downam <hi>de Anti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>christo.</hi> Willet <hi>Spnops.</hi>
                        </note> who convince that Church, some of scores, some of hundreds, some of five hundred Errors and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies. All they who grace that Church with the title of a <hi>true Church,</hi> must needs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend her to be so either in the first sense, or in the latter.</p>
                     <p>If in the first sense, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is nothing beholden to them: for they give her therein no prerogative above any heretical or schismatical church existent in the world: The <hi>truth of being</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to them all.</p>
                     <p>If in the latter sense, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches are less behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to them for by <hi>licking the blot of Heresie</hi> out of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121294:17"/>Church, they cast a <hi>foul blur</hi> of Schism upon all the Reformed Churches. There can be no <hi>medium</hi> given: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>heretical,</hi> and hath departed from the Faith of the ancient Church; or <hi>we</hi> are <hi>schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical</hi> who have forsaken her communion. Either the faith of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not justifiable; or our separation from her is not justifiable: For no man ought to sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the true Church of Christ, but hold good quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and correspondence with her. As we believe our Creed, so we ought to embrace in our practise the communion of Saints. The <hi>true Church</hi> of Christ is his mystical bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; from which whosoever i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121294:17"/>is divided from the Head, and consequently from all influence of his spirit: as the Author of the Sermons to the brethren in the desert, (supposed to be St. <hi>Austine</hi>) strongly inferreth, saying, <hi>Membrum amputatum non sequitur spiritus: cum in cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore erat, vivebat; precisum, amittit spiritum.</hi> The Life doth not runne in a member which is cut off: whilest it was a part of that body, it retained life; but being divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from it, it hath lost its spirits. With whom St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> agrees, <hi>Quisquis ab ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia segregatur, a promissis ecclesiae separatur: nec perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net ad Christi praemia, qui re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquit ecclesiam Christi. Ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enus est, prophanus est, host is
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121294:18"/>est. Habere jam non potest De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um patrem, qui ecclesiam non habet matrem.</hi> Whosoever is divided from the Church, he is separated from the promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses made to the Church: nor hath he any share in Christ's rewards, who leaves the Church of Christ. He is a stranger, he is profane, he is an enemy. He cannot call God his Father, who hath not the Church for his Mother. Were not <hi>Novatus,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Reynold <hi>prelect.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 6. <hi>error chfirmatus in haeresem evasit.</hi>
                        </note> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter him <hi>Donatus,</hi> deservedly branded with an indelible mark of <hi>Schism,</hi> for separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting themselves from the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church? and did not their Schism improved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in the end Heresie? I tremble to rehearse thedread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Sentence which St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:121294:18"/>pronounceth against all of the separation: <hi>Tales eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amsi occisi in confessione no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis Christi fuerint, macula ista nec sanguine abluitur. Esse martyr non potest, qui in ecclesia non est. Occidi potest, coronari non potest.</hi> Such persons are no Martyrs, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they lose their lives for confessing the Name of Christ: this stain will not be scowred clean, no not with blood. Killed they may be, but crowned they shall never be. And do they then good service to the Protestant Churches, who pluck the thorn of Heresie out of the foot of the Roman Church, and put as sharp, and a sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thorn of Schism into the foot of their own Mother?</p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:121294:19"/>
                     <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> the <hi>true Church</hi> is discerned by two notes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially, <hi>viz.</hi> the pure prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, and right administration of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; as is expresly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Art. 19. the <hi>Belgick</hi> Confession, Art. 20. the <hi>Augustan,</hi> Art. 7. the <hi>Saxon,</hi> Art. 11. <hi>Ecclesia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibilis est caetus fidelium, in quo verbum Dei purum praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catur, &amp; sacramenta (quo ad ea quae necessario exiguntur) juxta Christi institutum recte administrantur. i.e.</hi> The visi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church is the company of faithful Believers, among whom the pure word of God is preached, and the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments (according to those things which are truly requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>site)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121294:19"/>are rightly administred according to Christs institu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Belg <hi>His notis vera ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia a falsa discernitur, si in illa pura evangelis praedicatio, ligitima{que} sacramentorum ex Christi praescripto administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio vigeat.</hi> The <hi>true</hi> Church is disowned from the <hi>false</hi> by these marks; if therein the Gospel be purely preached, and the Sacraments rightly administred, according to the institution of Christ. Aug. <hi>Habet Ecclesia proprie dicta signa sua scilicet puram &amp; sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num evangelii doctrinam &amp; rectum usum sacramentorum.</hi> The Churrch, truly so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, hath two proper marks; <hi>viz.</hi> The pure and saving do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Gospel, and the right use of the Sacraments.
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121294:20"/>Sax. <hi>praecipue ex voce doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae judicandum est quae &amp; ubi sit vera ecclesia: quae voce ve rae doctrine, deinde &amp; legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo usu sacramentorum ab aliis discernitur.</hi> By the doctrine we may chiefly determine what, and where is the <hi>true church:</hi> w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> is discerned from the <hi>false</hi> ones by the sound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of doctrine, and the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful use of the Sacraments.</p>
                     <p>And it is most strongly confirmed by <hi>Whitaker Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lec. q.</hi> 5. <hi>Field</hi> of the Church, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>rton Apol. Cathol. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 38. <hi>Willet,</hi> Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies in <hi>Gen. de Notis Eccles. q.</hi> 4. Rivet, <hi>sum. controvers. tract.</hi> 2. <hi>q</hi> 7. <hi>Junius, Animad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers. in Bel. l.</hi> 4 <hi>controvers.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; deniceps Chemnis. ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amen, concil. Trid. p</hi> 49. <hi>&amp;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121294:20"/>part.</hi> 3. <hi>Locor. Theol p.</hi> 292. <hi>Mornaeus, tract. de Eccles c.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 15. But these marks are not to be found in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended church of <hi>Rome,</hi> but two contrary foul scars; <hi>viz.</hi> Impurity of doctrine, &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold corruption of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sacraments: see <hi>Hom.</hi> 16. <hi>in Penticost. Gallic. confes. art.</hi> 28. <hi>Papisticos conventos dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namus quod pura Dei veritas ab illis exulet: in quibus eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am sacramenta fidei corrupta sunt, adulterata, falsificata, vel poenitus etiam abolita:</hi> We condemn the Popish Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, because they have not the pure truth of God in them; and by reason that the Sacraments of faith are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thercorrupted, adulterated, &amp; falsified by them, or utterly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121294:21"/>abolished and rejected: For in the Roman Church, as it is at this day, the pure word of God is not preached, but partly Apochryphal Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, partly unwritten tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, are mixed with it. As for that pure Word of God which they preach (namely, the canonical Scriptures, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by both of us) they preach it not purely, but manifestly detort and pervert it, either by false translations, or glosses and interpretations in all points in controversie between us: And as for the Sacraments, they administer more by five then Christ e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver instituted for such, in the Gospel: And as for those that are instituted by him, they corruptly administer them;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121294:21"/>for they defile Baptism with cream and spittle, and divers superstitious rites: And they violate the Lords H. Supper, by taking away the cup from the Laity, and the substance of both elements, bread and wine, and quite overthrowing the nature thereof of a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, making it a private mass; and of a Sacrament, a Sacrifice, properly so called.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> The church of <hi>Rome</hi> can in no true sense challenge to her self the title of a <hi>true Church:</hi> for questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onless, that can be no <hi>true Church,</hi> which neither teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth nor practiseth the <hi>truth,</hi> which is sometimes taken in holy Scripture, <hi>pro veritate substantiae,</hi> for substantial truth: so called, in opposition
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121294:22"/>to the types, figures, and sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows of the Law: ometimes <hi>pro veritate doctrinae,</hi> for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinal truth, opposite to all errors and heresies in matters of faith: Sometimes <hi>pro ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate morali,</hi> for moral truth or honesty, opposite to fraud, dissimulation &amp; lying. Speak we of any of these three, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, the Roman church either hath it not, or not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely.</p>
                     <p>Not the first, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/>
                        <hi>Veritatem substantia,</hi> the truth of sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance: For the presence of the body necessarily exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the shadows: but the church of <hi>Rome</hi> at this day retaineth many legal shadows and figures, as the year of Jubile, consecration of Oyl, Altars, properly so called, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121294:22"/>a material and sensible Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, the Aronical Mitre and Vestments, and other the like <hi>Beggarly Rudiments</hi> of the Law, wherewith she endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vou eth to <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tch the seamless coat of Christ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Not the second: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> for the Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to which we have all subscribed, and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies confirmed in the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, charge the church of <hi>Rome</hi> with errour in matter of faith. So we read Article 19. the church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, not only in their living, &amp; and maner of ceremonies; but also <hi>in matter of faith.</hi> And in the Hom. for <hi>Whitsunday,</hi> second part, <hi>If it be possible the Spirit of Truth should be there where the true church
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121294:23"/>is not, then is it at</hi> Rome. And again, <hi>The church of</hi> Rome, <hi>as it is at this present, is not built upon the foundation of the Apostles and Prophets, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the sound and pure do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Jesus Christ.</hi> And Apologie of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> c. 16. Divis. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> p 6. <hi>We are gone from that church, which Christ, who cannot err, told so long before should err.</hi> With whom accordeth the French church in her confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, set down in the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of Protestant churches, Article 28. <hi>Papisticos conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus damnamus, quoa pura Dei veritas ab illis exulet, &amp;c.</hi> We condemn the Popish Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, because she shutteth her eyes against the pure truth of God, &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:121294:23"/>
                     <p>And as little can be said for her <hi>moral truth:</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> For (to speak nothing of the power which she maintaineth, in the Pope to dispence with the breach of Oathes and Vows, be they never so solemn and sacred) <hi>Navarrus,</hi> comment. in cap. human. aures: <hi>Farsons</hi> Mitigation, c. 7. <hi>Eudemon Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes,</hi> in his Apology for <hi>Garnet: Greg de Val.</hi> upon <hi>Thomas Southwell,</hi> and divers other Jesuits, have lately raked out of the ashes, or rather cin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars of hell, the heresie of the <hi>Priscillianists, Qui dogmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabant mendacium:</hi> Who taught lies for sound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. For they teach, That a man may speak, nay swear, that which is false, in words, so he salve it with
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121294:24"/>some mental reservation: for example, a Romish Priest may take his corporal Oath that he is no seminary Priest, reserving in his minde, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Apollo:</hi> That the Pope is not head of the church, reserving in his minde, a head of brass, like that set over <hi>Brasen-nose</hi> colledge. Neither is this a proper <hi>scar</hi> of the Jesuits on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but a foul <hi>mark</hi> of the whole Roman church also: For the secular Priests among them, as well as the Jesuits, are for this new art of lying, called <hi>equivocation:</hi> though they would not have it to be used hand overhead, but these their <hi>Reservations</hi> to be <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served</hi> for special use in some cases. There is no question to be made of it: such <hi>Watson</hi>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:121294:24"/>in his <hi>Quodlibits,</hi> Quodl. 3. Art. 4. but that in some sense, and in some cases, doubtful answers &amp; equivocations may be lawful: and the Treaties above cited of the Jesuits, were set forth with publique approbation: neither hath the Pope, nor the church of <hi>Rome</hi> by any publique brief, canon, or decree, branded this Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suitical art as impious and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to the Law of God, and light of nature.</p>
                     <p>Lastly, I cannot conceive how the malignant, and <hi>true</hi> militant church of Christ, can consist in one and the same Society, no more than <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon</hi> and the Ark, light and darkness, Christ and <hi>Belial:</hi> for they are not only <hi>diversae,</hi> but <hi>adversae,</hi> or opposite. But
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121294:25"/>the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is the malignant church, and hath so been for many hundreds of years, having put to death (as appeareth in the Rubricks of Ecclesiastical calenders) many thousands of true pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors, under the name of Dulcinests, Waldenses, Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genses, Wicklifests, Hussites, Hugonots, Calvinists, Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, and Protestants. If all the water in <hi>Tybris</hi> cannot wash away the stains of blood wherewith the garment of the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> is spotted, they may wel blush for shame who stile this scarlet Strum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, the <hi>true Spouse of Christ:</hi> for whom yet they plead, though (like a Lawyer that hath taken a light fee) very weakly and coldly.</p>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:121294:25"/>
                     <p>First, they argue thus, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">obj. </seg>1</label>
                        <q>
                           <hi>Ens &amp; verum convertuntur:</hi> i.e. <hi>being</hi> and <hi>true,</hi> are converti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble terms one with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and every thing which hath a being, is truly that being which it is, in truth of substance. A very Thief (say they) is a <hi>true man</hi> in the verity of his essence, as he is a reasonable creature; for this none can steal from him, nor he from himself, but death: But the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> be she never so corrupt in faith &amp; manners, is confessed to be a visible Christian Church; <label type="milestone">
                              <seg type="milestoneunit">sol. </seg>
                           </label>
                           <hi>ergo</hi> a true Church.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is to <hi>overdo,</hi> and so far to <hi>over-reach themselves,</hi> that they lame their arm, and thereby lessen their own
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121294:26"/>stroke. The more they seem to say, the less indeed they say for the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> In flying to a Metaphysick-truth, they in effect acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her to be destitute of Theological. If out of the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of their charity, they will extend a <hi>true Church</hi> so far as <hi>verum &amp; ens,</hi> i.e. true, and being, will go; all the Conventicles of Arians, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storians, Socinians, Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists, &amp; Familists, <hi>will come in for a share in the true Church:</hi> For they are all compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of men and women, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the Christian faith; they are all Churches, and (if this <hi>metaphysical string crack not) true Churches:</hi> Nay, by this reason, <hi>Pseudolus,</hi> the arrantest cheater in theworld,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121294:26"/>may be proved to be a true man: <hi>Messalina,</hi> the most notorious Strumpet that ever lay by Princes side, a true wife: <hi>Nero,</hi> that monster of men, a good man: The De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil himself, both a true, and a good Angel: For as <hi>Ens &amp; verum,</hi> i.e. being, and true, so <hi>Ens &amp; bonum,</hi> i. e. being, and good, are convertible terms; and they may as soon prove by this argument, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a <hi>good Church,</hi> as to be a <hi>true;</hi> which palpable absurdities, &amp; gross inconveniences, they can no otherwise avoid, then by ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting away the former argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; which like an Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an reed, if it be leaned upon, breaketh, and runneth into their own sides. The truth is,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121294:27"/>This Argument (how much soever it is made of by many) is no better then a meer fala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, or Syllogism, consisting of four terms. For <hi>truth,</hi> as it is applied to <hi>Ens,</hi> or being, <hi>in genere,</hi> or generally, in the major; or as it is applied to <hi>Ecclesia,</hi> or Church, which is a determinate species of <hi>Ens,</hi> or being, is not one and the self same tearm. <hi>Truth,</hi> as it is applied in the major, to the genus, signifieth no more then <hi>veritatem entis,</hi> or <hi>existen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> truth of being or exist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; but in the conclusion, as it is applied to the <hi>Church,</hi> it signifieth <hi>veritatem entis tales,</hi> the <hi>truth</hi> of such a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: to which more is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red then to <hi>Ens in genere,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e. being, in general. And as it
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121294:27"/>will not follow, the Devil is a true creature; <hi>Ergo,</hi> a true Angel; or <hi>Messalina</hi> is a true woman, <hi>ergo,</hi> a true wife; so neither will it follow, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is <hi>verus cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> or <hi>verum ens,</hi> i. e. a true company, or true being, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, <hi>Vera ecclesia, i. e.</hi> a <hi>true Church.</hi> The argument wil no way follow from truth in <hi>sensu metaphisico,</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> e. in a metaphysical sense; to a truth in <hi>sensu thealogico,</hi> i. e. in a theological sense: no more then it will follow from truth in <hi>sensu physico,</hi> i.e. in physi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal sense, to truth in <hi>sensu mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale,</hi> or, in a moral sense. As if a man should conclude, the great Thief <hi>Harpulus</hi> is a true man, in <hi>sensu physico,</hi> or in a physical sense: for he hath
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121294:28"/>the essence of a man, therefore he is a true man in <hi>sensu mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rale,</hi> that is, an honest man. This first argument of theirs therefore, is like a false string in an instrument, which can never be tuned to make any good musick.</p>
                     <p>The 2<seg rend="sup">d</seg>
                        <hi>string</hi> is not much better: <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">obj. </seg>2</label> which they thus <hi>strain,</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Where there is true bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism, there is a true church: But in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> there is true baptism, confessed on all hands, for those which are baptized in that Church, we rebaptize not; <hi>ergo,</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a true Church.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>In this Argument, they <hi>scower up the old harness of the Donatists.</hi> August. l 1. de Bap. cont. Dona. c. 10. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:121294:28"/>they thus fought against the Catholick Church
<q>How could we (say they) gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate &amp; bring forth children to the Church (which you confess we do by our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism) if we were not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and a <hi>true Church,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Austine</hi> answereth that, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">sol. </seg>
                        </label>
                        <hi>They who separated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves from others, breaking the bond of unity and charity, if they retained nothing of all those things in the former so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,</hi> in omnibus separatisunt, <hi>then they were utterly, and in each part, separated from the Church: But if they retained some things which were the same,</hi> non se in iis separave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, <hi>then in those things they did not sever themselves
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121294:29"/>from the Church;</hi> &amp; ex ea parte intexturae compage de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ur, <hi>in that part wherein they retained the same, they were fastned, and held to the Church in that joynt, though in others severed: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he whom they gathered to themselves,</hi> ex ea parte ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctitur Ecclesiae, in qua nec illi separati sunt, <hi>is joyned to the Church on that part wherein themselves are not disjoyned.</hi> And after this, applying it to the former question, he saith, That <hi>hereticks generate chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to the Church, by that wherein they are joyned to the Church; not by that wherein they are severed from it They are severed from the band of charity and peace, but they are joyned in one baptism.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:121294:29"/>
                     <p>Yet, to <hi>hew,</hi> and further to <hi>batter in pieces</hi> this <hi>harness</hi> of the Donatists, I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer particularly to each pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position: And first to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor;</p>
                     <p>It is most certain, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> that true baptism cannor be severed from the <hi>true Church;</hi> yet is not baptism so proper to the <hi>true Church,</hi> but that it may be found in a false and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Church: as S. <hi>Austine</hi> accutely observes, that the <hi>Rivers of Paradise ran out of Paradise.</hi> Wheresoever the <hi>true Church</hi> is, there is true baptism, but not <hi>vice versa.</hi> Wheresoever is true baptism, there is the <hi>true Church:</hi> for much more is required to the <hi>true Church,</hi> then true bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism onely: There must be in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121294:30"/>it the true preaching of the Word, at least, in all funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental points; and the right administration of both the Sacraments. Saint <hi>Austine</hi> makes no bones, <hi>totidem ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> to deny the <hi>major,</hi> de bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cont. Donat. l. 6 c. 23. <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siam sicut habent eacholici non habent heretici, &amp; tamen bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismum habent: Ita{que} sicut po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testbaptisma esse, &amp; unde se au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret spiritus sanctus. ita potest baptisma esse ubi non est eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sia.</hi> Heret cks have not the Church, as Catholicks have, and yet they have baptism. Therefore, as there may be a baptism from which the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghost may withdraw him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, so there may be a bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism where the Church is not. <hi>Et cap.</hi> 16. <hi>Non omnes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121294:30"/>qui tenent baptismum, tenent ecclesiam: sicut non omnes qui tenent ecclesiam, tenent &amp; vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam eternam.</hi> All that hold with baptism, do not hold with the Church; as all do not hold eternal life, who hold baptism. <hi>Et c.</hi> 7 <hi>Baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum legitimum habent, sed non legitime habent.</hi> They hold baptism lawful, but they use it not lawfully.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> to the <hi>minor</hi> I answer, That though in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> there is <hi>true baptism, quo ad legitimam formam verborum,</hi> according to the true prescribed form of words by Christ: and therefore is not to be reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, because it hath all in it that is essentially required to baptism: yet is it not <hi>true
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121294:31"/>baptism, quo ad purum ritum,</hi> according to the pure rite: much less <hi>quo ad salutarem effectum,</hi> according to the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving effect.</p>
                     <p>It is not true baptism, according to the pure rite and manner of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration thereof (for they mingle water with cream, salt and spittle: and thereby, as much as in them lieth, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file this most holy <hi>Laver;</hi> and according to their own Tenets, they <hi>set this seal to a blank.</hi> For whereas bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism is the seal of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousness of faith, and the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of grace, they deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this righteousness of faith, consequently <hi>set this seal to a blank.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> Neither is their baptism
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121294:31"/>true, <hi>quo ad salutarem ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum, i. e.</hi> according to the saving effect. For so St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> expresly teacheth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Baptism of all Hereticks, <hi>l. de Vinco. Bapt. cont. Petil. c.</hi> 6. <hi>Nihil prodest hereticis ad salutem, quod ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ecclesiam verum baptis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum pignorantium &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dunt &amp; tenent.</hi> It is no way advantagious to the salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Hereticks, that though they are out of the Church, yet they hold Baptism, and make use thereof. <hi>Et l.</hi> 4. <hi>cont. Donat. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Ecclesia Paradiso comparata indicat nobis, posse quidem ejus bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tismum homines etiam fores accipere; sed salutem beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudines extra eam neminem vel percipere, vel tenere. Ita
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121294:32"/>fit ut cum Paradisi aqua sit extra Paradisum; beatitudo tamen non sit nisi intra Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radisum: Sic ergo Baptismus ecclesia potest esse extra ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiam munus autem beatae vitae, non nisi intra ecclesiam reperitur.</hi> The Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compared to Paradise, teacheth us, that even men that are out of the Church may retain the Baptism of the Church; but none out of the Church can partake of the blessed Salvation. Hence it cometh to pass, that although the streams of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter do run out of Paradise, yet Salvation is to be had onely in Paradise. So also the Baptism of the Church may be administred out of the Church, but the blessing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:121294:32"/>of eternal Life is no where to be found but within the church.</p>
                     <p>They also lay great stress upon this Argument, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">obj. </seg>3</label> which is as weak as the former, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>The church of <hi>Rome</hi> is no worse then the church of <hi>Israel,</hi> under the revolted kingdom of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and his Successors, who erected Calves in <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel,</hi> which they went a whoring after; Yet notwithstanding this defection from the true Worship of God, because they continued a profession of God, and of the Law, and retained the holy Seals of his Covenant, they were even then a part of the <hi>true</hi> visible <hi>church</hi> of God, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:121294:33"/>tearmed Gods people, and his children. Therefore the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> though ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry corrupt in faith and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, must be accounted a true church of God.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hereunto I answer, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">sol. </seg>1</label> That the case of the Roman church is worse then that of the ten Tribes: For they committed Idolatry but in one kinde, the church of <hi>Rome</hi> in many: the corruption and idolatry in them was practised <hi>de facto,</hi> but not solemnly ratified by any Decree or Canon of their whole Church, as the super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition and idolatry of the Romish church are.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> Those who wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped <hi>Jeroboams</hi> Calves, without repentance could not be saved; for <hi>no Idolater shall
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121294:33"/>enter into the Kingdom of God,</hi> saith the Apostle.
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 6.9, 10.</note> The Prophets which were sent to the ten Tribes, style that Common-wealth a <hi>Harlot,</hi> and her children <hi>bastard chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> and as a Harlot before she be divorced, is a wife, but not a true and loyal wife; so was the church of <hi>Israel</hi> in those days: and so now we grant the church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be, a <hi>church,</hi> but not a <hi>true church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> If any of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient or later Divines say, there was the <hi>true church</hi> of God among the <hi>ten Tribes,</hi> because they had true Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets among them, and the true Word of God, and the Sacraments appointed by him; their words are to be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121294:34"/>understood, not of the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward face of that church, and prevalent part in it which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to <hi>Jeroboam</hi> and the Calves, as they were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipped, the Calves he set up; but of those many thousands which God reserved to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self within those Dominions, who never bowed the knee to <hi>Baal,</hi> neither lift up their hands to the golden calves: these we grant were members of the true church, as are all such who even in <hi>Rome</hi> it self and other parts, subject to the Pope, live among Papists, and communicate with them in common Acts and Duties of Christianity, but partake not with them in their here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Tenents, or idolatrous and superstitious Rites. We
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121294:34"/>owe a clearer manifestation of the truth in this point, to the candor of B. <hi>Whitgift,</hi> who in the Defence of his Answer to the Admonition, <hi>p.</hi> 625. thus paralelleth the Papists and <hi>Israelites:</hi>
                        <q>The Papist (saith he) are like the <hi>Israelites</hi> under <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> for as those <hi>Israelites,</hi> so Papists pretend the Law of God, use the Sacraments, profess Christianity, and are not in all points straying from Christian Faith; but yet have corrupted the same with idolatrous worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, and divers other kinde of superstitions and errors.</q> Therefore <hi>Beza</hi> said very well. <hi>Ecclesia est velut im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mersa in papatu.</hi> The church is as it were covered, or
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:121294:35"/>drowned in Papisme.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">obj. </seg>4</label> They seem also much to triumph in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Antichrist sitteth in the Temple of God.
<note place="margin">2 Thes. 2.4. <hi>shewing himself that he is God.</hi>
                           </note> By the Temple of God is here meant the true church: But the Pope is Antichrist: <hi>Ergo</hi> the church of <hi>Rome</hi> in which he sits, as in the Temple of God, is a true church.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>With this weapon they do but <hi>flourish,</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>See An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the</hi> Gagg.</note> they <hi>fight not in good earnest;</hi> for they who thus argue, believe not the Pope to be Antichrist. They finde seven hills at <hi>Constanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople,</hi> and Antichrist at the <hi>Seraglia:</hi> Yet, if as the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Peter Lumbard,</hi> chose rather to be
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121294:35"/>accounted a strumpet; then not to be held the <hi>true mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> of those great Clerks; so in <hi>sober sadness</hi> they will rather yield <hi>Rome</hi> to be <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> and the Pope to be Antichrist, then not have the church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged a true church.</p>
                     <p>I further answer, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it seems to me most probable, that by the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God the Apostle mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth not the Temple at <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem,</hi> which was soon after he wrote this Epistle destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and is likely never to be built again, but the church of God, as <hi>Austine,</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome,</hi> and St. <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> and <hi>Theodoret,</hi> and <hi>Primasius,</hi> and <hi>Calvin</hi> himself, and <hi>Beza</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solve on this Text: yet this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121294:36"/>Interpretation will little, or nothing at all help the cause. I subscribe fully to St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> l. 20. <hi>De Civitat. Dei,</hi> c. 19. and St. <hi>Jerome</hi> in his q. 11. <hi>ad Algasiam,</hi> That <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist shall fit in the church of God:</hi> and to <hi>Severianus</hi> alledged by <hi>Orcumenius,</hi> that the Apostle speaks not of the temple of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> but the church of God: or rather to St. <hi>Chrysostom,</hi> That <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ shall command himself to be worshipped in the stead of God, not onely at</hi> Jerusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>but also in the churches:</hi> And to <hi>Theodoret,</hi> He <hi>calleth the temple of God the church in which Antichrist shall arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate unto himself the chief Seat, endeavouring to shew himself as God:</hi> And to <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact,</hi>
                        <pb n="59" facs="tcp:121294:36"/>He <hi>sitteth not in the temple, which is</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>especially; but simply in the churches, and in every temple of God:</hi> And to <hi>Calvin,</hi> comment. in Ep. ad Thessal. That <hi>the Apostle calleth the Den of so many superstitions,</hi> (viz. <hi>the Roman church</hi>) <hi>the temple of God, because there is a</hi> residium, <hi>a remainder still of the Proprieties of the church among them, in regard whereof it is the temple of God, though profaned:</hi> And to <hi>Beza, Predicit Apostolus Antichristum, id est quisquis sedem illam Apostolicam oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupavit, non regnaturum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra ecclesiam, sed in ecclesiae sinu: i. e.</hi> That by the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple is understood the church of God, in which the man of
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121294:37"/>sin sitteth, usurping the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion thereof. <hi>Appellatione Templi Dei significatur ipsa ecclesia, in qua homo ille per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditus etiam nunc sedet, impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam fibi usurpans.</hi> And I hold, from this very Text it may be demonstrated, that the great Antichrist whom the Apostle here sets out in his colours, shall not be a Jew, Turk, Pagan, or Infidel, but a professed Christian, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siding in <hi>the bosome of the church.</hi> And yet I deny the Rhemists consequence here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, That therefore the church of <hi>Rome</hi> must be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the true church, and the Pope a member thereof. For though the wild Bore break into the Lords vineyard, and be in the midst
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121294:37"/>of it, rooting up the choicest plants; yet he is no part of the vineyard: and though the wolf get into the flock, <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying Christs Lambs,</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring his fattest sheep, yet he is not any part of the flock. To rebate therefore the edge, and turn the point of the former Argument upon the adversary, I say:</p>
                     <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> That the Apostle calleth the Seat of Antichrist the temple or church of God, because it was so: as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour calleth the temple of <hi>Jerusalem</hi> the holy place, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.15. because it had been so, although at that time wherein that <hi>abominable desolation should stand there,</hi> (which he prophesied of) it was a most detestable place;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121294:38"/>namely, when the Romans came to destroy it: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> we often call the dead Corpses of a man, by his name whose sometimes it was before it fell to be a carcase. So is the Popes See called the Temple of God, in regard of what it was before he set his seat there. For after he fixed his throne there, it became <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedra pestilentia,</hi> Babylon, <hi>and spiritual</hi> Sodom, <hi>and an habitation of devils, and the hold of every foul spirit, and a cage of every unclean and hateful bird,</hi> Apoc. 18.2.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> That the place where Antichrist sitteth as God, boasting himself that he is God, may be taken for the true Church of God, and yet the present Roman church
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:121294:38"/>never the nearer. For it is certain, that the Pope hath his seat in the very heart of the Catholicke Christian Church; and that he chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lengeth a kinde of Divine Sovereignty over the whole church; and most of all exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciseth his tyranny upon the sincere Professors of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel, who are the found mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the true Church.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, As a Temple, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> though it be profaned and polluted, and in part ruined, is yet a Temple in respect of the Dedication to Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and divers parts of Gods Worship truly performed in it: so even the Roman church it self, as it consisteth of the Pope and his adherents, who bear all the sway in it, may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121294:39"/>truely bee said to bee a church of Christ, in regard of the profession of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity in it, though not a true and Orthodox church: As neither can we tearm a Temple after it is de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>led, or in decay, a pure and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Temple before it be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged and repaired. And upon these tearmes all the learned Protestants, who have wrote upon this point, will come in, and easily be reconciled. Those who deny her to be a Church, exclude her not simply from being at all of the church; but from being <hi>in Orthodoxei,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire profession of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, a <hi>true church.</hi> Those who style her a <hi>true church,</hi> mean no more then a
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121294:39"/>truly visible company, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessing the Christian Faith. <hi>When</hi> (saith <hi>Calvin,</hi> Institut. l. 4. c. 2.) <hi>we refuse abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely to grant the title of the Church unto Papists, we do not therefore deny that there are churches among them, but we strive for the true and lawful constitution of the church, whose communion in prayer and doctrine is to be kept.</hi> And a little after, <hi>See<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the See of Antichrist, or of the Pope, is placed in the temple of God, it is thereby signified, that his reign shall be such as doth neither abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish, nor take from the name of Christians, or the church. Wherefore it is manifest that we do not deny but that chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches remain under the Popes
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121294:40"/>tyranny, though prophaned with sacrilegious Impiety.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> in 1 <hi>Kings c.</hi> 12. propoundeth this que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion to himself, Whether since the Papacy erected, there be a church among Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists? And he answereth, <hi>That the church was then sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, and dayly is more and more ruinated; so that there remains no more then</hi> rudera &amp; frustra parietum, <hi>certain broken pieces, and rubbish of the wall. Wherefore we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge their Baptism, we reverence and read the same sacred books as they do; and thus we understand Antichrist to sit in the temple of God, because it was once so, and as yet retaineth</hi> quaedam eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siae vestigia, <hi>certain points of the church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="67" facs="tcp:121294:40"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Reynolds</hi> and <hi>Hooker,</hi> very eminent men both in their kinde, dealing against adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries most differently affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the one sort arrogating too much, the other yielding too little to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> against them both concur in this truth, That though it be neither the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick church, nor a sound member thereof, yet it is a member. <hi>Reynold</hi> Thes 5. <hi>Romana ecclesia nec est catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, nec sanum membrum ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae ecclesiae;</hi> yet that it is a part of the visible church, though maimed; and a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, though unsound. <hi>Hoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker</hi> Ecclesiast. Pol. l. 5. c. 68. l. 3. c. 1. For <hi>apparent it is</hi> (saith <hi>Hooker</hi>) <hi>that all men are of necessity either chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121294:41"/>or not christians. If by external profession they be christians (as all Papists are) they are of the visible church of Christ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <q>A Church (saith <hi>Philip Morney</hi>) may be so far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with heresies, that from the crown of the head to the sole of the foot, there may be nothing sound and whole, and yet so long as they are heretical, they do not cease to be the churches of Christ, no more then a man ceaseth to be a man by reason of some great sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness. Nay, even hereby it may be proved that they are still churches, because they are heretical in the doctrine of Christ; no otherwise then we know by the Diseases
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:121294:41"/>wherewith one is effected or pained, that he is a live man, and not a dead corpse. But if any fall from heresie to infidelity, and a total de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial of the Faith, then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed they cease to be chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</q> And afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying this, which generally concerns all impure and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt churches, to the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> he truly calleth it <hi>Omnium impurissimam, &amp; per aliis omnibus quae ad huc fuerunt hereticam:</hi> Of all most impure, placed in a more eminent degree of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror then all the rest; and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical above all that ever yet were: yea such as is univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sally distempered, and hath so heaped heresies upon he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resies, that it may seem ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121294:42"/>to be a Disease it self, then fallen into diseases. Yet of this Romane he saith, <hi>Quamdiu vel tenue illud filum reliquum manet ecclesiae no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, non denegamus,</hi> &amp;c. We deny not unto it the name of a church, so long as it holds by this slender threed; as we deny not him the name of a man, who lives, though in a languishing consumption.</p>
                     <p>Lastly, Doctor <hi>Craken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorp</hi> in his most learned and accurate <hi>Defence of the church of</hi> England, against the revolted Archbishop of <hi>Spallatta,</hi> cap. 16. <hi>This your Roman Church</hi> (saith he) <hi>must be accounted both to be in the church, and to be a church, not simply, nor according to the integrity of the faith, nor
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121294:42"/>according to any inward ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; nor so effectually, that it should avail to salvation for a man to be in it: but yet a church it is in some respects, according to the external pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fession of faith, and of the word of God, and according to the administration of the Sacraments, and according to some doctrines of true belief; by which, as by so many out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ligaments, she is yet knit to the Orthodox and Cathelick Church</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Fifthly, They dispute thus: <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">obj. </seg>5</label>
                        <list>
                           <item>Out of the <hi>true church</hi> there is no salvation:</item>
                           <item>But in the Roman church there is salvation:
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Ergo,</hi> the Roman church is the <hi>true church.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:121294:43"/>
                     <p>That out of the true church there is no salvation, they confirm by the testimony of St. <hi>Cyprian: Non potest ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere Deum patrem, qui Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiam non habet matrem:</hi> He cannot have God to his Father, who acknowledgeth not the Church for his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And by an Argument rather typick then topick,
<list>
                           <item>The Ark was a type of the church:</item>
                           <item>But out of the Ark none were saved from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge:</item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Ergo,</hi> out of the church none are saved from the <hi>gulph of destruction,</hi> but are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly <hi>drowned in perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>The assumption they make good out of the confession
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121294:43"/>of many learned Protestants: Of <hi>Luther,</hi> l. de Serm. arbit. Of <hi>Morney,</hi> tract de Eccles. c. 9. <hi>George Abbot.</hi> Answer to <hi>Hull.</hi> Reason 1. Sect. 30. <hi>Hooker</hi> l. 3. Ecclesias. Polit. Sect. 1. &amp; concio. in <hi>Abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuck</hi> 1. <hi>Field,</hi> of the church. l. 3. c. 47. <hi>Morton,</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Appeal. lib. 4. cap. 1. &amp; Grand Impost. cap. 15. And if any rest not satisfied with these concurrent Judgements of learned Protestants, they put weak consciences to the rack with these, or the like Interrogatories, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        <q>What think you? Were all the Founders of Colledges and Halls, all the Kings and Princes of these Realmes, nay all your Grand-fathers, and Great Grand-fathers,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121294:44"/>who lived before the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation in <hi>Luthers</hi> time, damned, and now fry in the flames of Hell?</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Because with this kinde of reasoning they prevail much with men of a tender consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">sol. </seg>
                        </label> and charitable disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; of whom we may truly say, as <hi>Paterculus</hi> doth of <hi>Cato, Optimo animo nocuit Reipublicae:</hi> Out of a pious minde and good nature, they so resolve the former doubt, that they some way wrong and prejudice the Protestant Cause. I will put this fair Piece of Coyn, currant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong very many, to the Test of a more particular Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, then hath yet been done by any to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:121294:44"/>
                     <p>First therefore, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> I retort the Argument upon the Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary, that he may thereby ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feel the strength of it against himself, or see the weakness thereof as it is ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged against us.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>'Out of the true church 'there is no salvation:</item>
                        <item>'But out of the Roman church there is salvation:</item>
                        <item>'<hi>Ergo,</hi> the Roman church is 'not the true church.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>In this Syllogism the <hi>major</hi> is theirs. The assumption they will not deny, unless they will confess either that they are within the Roman church, or are out of the state of salvation. To say nothing of the Greek Churches un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Patriarch of <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:121294:45"/>and the Egyptians under the Patriarch of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> and infinite other Christian churches in <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca</hi> and <hi>Asia,</hi> which (as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetus</hi> a Popish Cosmogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher confesseth) are so far from subjection to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man church, that they know not whether there be any such or no; and (yet I am sure these men will not <hi>cast the Dy upon their salvation</hi>) let them look to it, how they can keep off the conclusion, <hi>viz.</hi> The Roman church is not the <hi>true church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> I answer by way of distinction of the tearms, of which this Argument con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisteth; of which are, 1. Out of the true church. 2. Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. 3. The Roman church.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <pb n="77" facs="tcp:121294:45"/>1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> A man may be said to be out of the <hi>church</hi> in a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble sense:</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Either because he is <hi>out of the communion</hi> of the Church.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Or because he is <hi>out of the pale,</hi> confines, or jurisdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of any church.</p>
                     <p>A church may be said to be <hi>true.</hi> 1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> Either simply and universally, namely such a church as holdeth no error at all in any point that tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth upon salvation, or is necessary to be required to be believed by any Christian <hi>implicitè,</hi> or <hi>explicitè;</hi> but maintaineth entirely all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick truths in this nature. 2. <hi>Secundum quid,</hi> or in part; namely such a church as hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth no error in such points
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121294:46"/>as are absolutely necessary to salvation; and all men are bound explicitely to believe, under pain of Damnation: such as are the first principles of Divinity, and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Articles of our Christian Belief.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> When there is a que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion of Salvation, the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may be,
<list>
                           <item>1. Either of the <hi>possibility, viz.</hi> whether in such a church salvation by any means may possibly be had?</item>
                           <item>2. Or of the <hi>certainty of Salvation;</hi> whether by the holding of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of that church, and living conformable there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, a man shall certainly &amp; undoubtedly be saved?</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:121294:46"/>
                     <p>The Roman church may be, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iv."/>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. Either taken for all chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches professing the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Faith in <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> and other countreys subject to the Popes Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risdiction:</item>
                           <item>2. Or for the outward face of the Roman church, holding Pope <hi>Pius</hi> his Creed, affixed to the Council of <hi>Trent;</hi> and maintaining and practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing all the idolatrous and superstitious Rites enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Pope and his Cardinals.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>According to these Distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, in full satisfaction of the former Argument, I set down these Assertions fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, which weaken all the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121294:47"/>sinews, and loosen the joynts thereof, <hi>viz.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/>
                        <hi>A man may be saved who is out of the confines or jurisdiction of any Church.</hi> For a true Believer in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derness, or under the Pole, or in <hi>Japan,</hi> or <hi>China,</hi> or in any part out of the Christian world, among the Pagans and Infidels may be saved: yet no man can be saved out of the communion of the <hi>true church</hi> of Christ, either actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al and in profession, or at least virtual, or in desire: For all that are saved, must believe the communion of Saints, and be members of Christs mystical body, and have some fellowship both with the Head, and other members. And this is the meaning of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121294:47"/>Saint <hi>Cyprian,</hi> That such he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks or schismaticks who renounce all communion with the church their mother, so long as they continue in that minde, cannot have God to be their father.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> Out of <hi>the true church in the first sense (that is, a church which holdeth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely all doctrines of Faith, implicitely or explicitely, to be believed, as principles or conclusions deducted from them) there may be had sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> but out of a true church in the second sense there can be ordinarily no salvation. For a sound be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief in all such fundamental Points, is absolutely necessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the very essence of a church: and where there is
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121294:48"/>absolutely no church, there is no calling by the Word and Sacraments: and where no such calling, no ordinary meanes of Salvation. But where these Doctrines are taught (though many perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious errors by consequence overthrowing the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, are held) there may be Salvation. For it is very possible that those who live in such a corrupt church, may (with the <hi>Bereans</hi>) examine the Doctrine of their Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers by the Scriptures, and embrace such Doctrines as their Teachers propound un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them agreeable thereunto, and reject those that are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, as many thousands did in the Arian churches,
<note place="margin">Hilar. cont. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                              <desc>••••</desc>
                           </gap>ent.</note>
                        <hi>whose eares were purer then the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121294:48"/>mouthes of their Teachers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/>
                        <hi>In a very corrupt church there must be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged a possibility of salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but no certainty and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallibility</hi> our of a pure and orthodox church. A possi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of salvation cannot be denied the ignorant especial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, because they hold the foundation, and survey not the Building: and the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation can deceive no man that rests upon it. But a se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure way they cannot goe where they meet with such corruptions.</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>Now wisdom there can be none, in such a point as salvation is, to forsake a church in which there is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of salvation, to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a church in which there
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121294:49"/>is a bare possibility.</q> Nay St. <hi>Austine</hi> (l. 1. de Bapt. cont. Donat. c. 3. <hi>Graviter peccarent in rebus ad salutem animae pertinentibus eo solo quod certa in certis prepone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: i. e.</hi> they should grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vously sin in matters concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the salvation of their souls, if they prefer things doubtful before things cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain) chargeth them with a great sin, who in point of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation preferre uncertainties and naked possibilities, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an evident and certain course.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iv."/>
                        <hi>There may be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of salvation to many thousands of christians, who live within the circuit of the Popes Jurisdiction, and have communion with the Roman
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121294:49"/>church in common points of Christianity, so they joyn not with her in her errors and su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitions.</hi> And farther we cannot deny a possibility of salvation to those who held many of her errours, (as no doubt many of our Ancest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors did) so long as they held the main foundation of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Doctrine, to wit, sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation onely by the merits of Christ (which all generally did before the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> as appears by the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do visitandi infirmos,</hi> allowed till then by the church of <hi>Rome</hi>) and asked God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveness at their death, of all their errours known or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known. But there can be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonably granted neither cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, nor possibility of sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:121294:50"/>to such as in the light of the Gospel (where they have means better to inform themselves) hold all the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and corruptions of the Roman church, and die in the explicite maintenance thereof. For the rule of the Apostle is most certain, no Idolater (remaining such, that is without repentance) shall inherit the kingdom of God. And (besides Heresies) the present church of <hi>Rome</hi> (that is, the prevalent faction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in) is justly charged by the Reformed churches with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold Idolatry.</p>
                     <p>Lastly, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">obj. </seg>6</label> They go about to obscure the matter with a cloud of Allegations and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stimonies; which yet is not so thick, but that the truth
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:121294:50"/>pierceth it, and breaketh through with her bright beams.</p>
                     <p>In the first place they set <hi>Luther</hi> against us,
<note place="margin">Ep. Pleb. &amp; Anabat</note> affirming in one of his Epistles, That <hi>there is in the Papacy true Scripture, true Baptism, the true Sacraments, much chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian good; nay all christian good: nay moreover, that under the Papacy is true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stianity;</hi> imo verus nucluus christianitatis, <hi>the very kernel of christianity.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Next, <hi>Calvin</hi> Instit. lib 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> cap. 2. Sect. 12. <hi>Hinc patet, nos minime negare quia sub Romani ontificis tryanide ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia maneant,</hi> we deny not but that there remain chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches under the tyranny of the Pope; whose seat is placed
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:121294:51"/>in the temple of God: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is intimated, that his kingdome shall be such, <hi>quod nec Christi, ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ecclesia no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men aboleat,</hi> as doth neither abolish, or take from the name of Christ, or of the Church.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Junius,</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> lib singular de ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles. <hi>Ecclesia Romana, qua id habet in se quod ad ecclesiae definitionem pertinet, est ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiae, i. e.</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as it hath in it that which belongs to the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a church, is a church.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Field,</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iv."/> the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is truly a Church</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Zanchius,</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v."/> Pref. l. de Nat. Dei. <hi>Satan could not in the very Roman church do what he listed, as he had done in the Eastern; to bring all
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:121294:51"/>things to such a pass, as that it should have no more the form of a christian church:</hi> And a little after, <hi>I do not assent to them which would have the church of</hi> Rome <hi>to have no less ceased to be the church of Christ, than those Eastern churches, which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards turned Mahumetan. What church was ever more corrupt then the church of the ten Tribes? yet we learn from the Scriptures, that it was still the church of God. And how doth St.</hi> Paul <hi>call that church wherein Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>christ shall sit, the temple of God? Neither is it any Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tism at all that is administred out of the church of Christ. The wife that is an adulteress, doth not cease to be a wife,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:121294:52"/>unless being despoiled of her Marriage-ring, she be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly divorced. The church of</hi> Rome <hi>therefore is yet the church of Christ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Doctor <hi>Crathenthorp,</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vi."/> tract. M. S. <hi>The church of</hi> Rome <hi>is a true, but unsound, visible church: for wheresoever the outward profession of Faith, and of the Word of God is found, among such as be uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Sacraments of Christ, and with that mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual duty which is betweene Pastours and their Flocks, the same cannot but be acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged for a visible church, or</hi> coetus vocatorum, <hi>such a society of men as are outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called to the participation of grace and glory.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord Bishop of <hi>Exon,</hi>
                        <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vii."/>
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:121294:52"/>in his Treatise called, <hi>The old Religion,</hi> cap. 1. <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal truth is like that</hi> Maro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean <hi>Wine, which if it be mixed with twenty times so much water, holds his strength The Sepulchre of Christ was overwhelmed by the Pagans without earth and rubbish, and more then so: over it they built a temple to their im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure</hi> Venus, <hi>yet still in spite of malice, there was the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of Christ. And it is a ruled case of</hi> Papinian, <hi>That a sacred place looseth not the holiness with the demolished walls, no more doth the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man loose the claim of a true visible church, by her mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold and deplorable corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And this testimony of his
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:121294:53"/>is backed with the Approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of two right Reverend, and most Learned Fathers in our Church, the Bishops of <hi>Duresm</hi> and <hi>Salisbury;</hi> and two Eminent Doctors, the Kings Professor at <hi>Oxford;</hi> and Doctor <hi>Primerose</hi> Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher to the French Church in <hi>London.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To answer unto, <label type="milestone">
                           <seg type="milestoneunit">sol. </seg>
                        </label> or rather interpret the above-alledged testimonies in order:</p>
                     <p>To the first, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> which is <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,</hi> I say, That though <hi>Luther</hi> in writing against the Anabaptists (who denied Baptism in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein <hi>Luther</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was christianed) had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son to make the best he could of that church; yet he attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buteth no more to it than
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:121294:53"/>Saint <hi>Austine,</hi> and other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do to the <hi>Donatists</hi> and other Hereticks, whom they acknowledge to have among them the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; which yet they held to be no way beneficial to their salvation, if they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted in their Schismes and Heresies; but would be then available unto them, when they should repent and return to the bosome of the true church. Neither doth <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> say, that <hi>papatus est omne bonum christianum,</hi> or <hi>nucle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us christianitatis;</hi> that the Papacy is all Christian good, or the kernel of Christianity: but, <hi>in,</hi> or <hi>sub papatu;</hi> in, or under the Papacy, is the true Creed, the true Decalogue, the true Lords Prayer, which
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:121294:54"/>he tearmeth the Kernel of Christianity. Wherein he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords with other Protestants, that by reason of these Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in the Roman church, God may have, and hath, his true church, even where An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichrist hath his seat: or that there are many true Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers throughout all the Popes jurisdiction; or (to use their own words) the Papacy is in the church and <hi>the church is in the papacy: yet the papacy is not the church, but a botch, or blain, or plague-sore in it, under which there is sound flesh; yet the plague sore is not the sound flesh</hi> For otherways, if we understand by the Roman church not the true Believers (which se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly in it worship God in
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:121294:54"/>spirit and truth, and mourn for those abuses which it is not in their power to reform) but the predominant Faction which adhereth to the Pope, and maintaineth all the Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors and Corruptions of that Church. <hi>Luther</hi> held the Roman church in that sense to be the <hi>whore of Babylon,</hi> and <hi>Synagogue of Antichrist,</hi> as he who lists may read in his Book, Entituled, <hi>Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitas Babylonica,</hi> and in his Answer to the Pop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s Bull, which he tearmeth, <hi>The exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable Bull of Antichrist.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the second, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> which is <hi>Calvins,</hi> I say, That if his testimony had been alledged entirely, it would have sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Alledgers. For though he deny not the title
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:121294:55"/>of a Church to Papists, yet in the same place he flatly denieth them the title of a <hi>true Church,</hi> which is the <hi>car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do questionis.</hi> His words are, <hi>Cum ergo Ecclesiae titulum non simpliciter volumus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedere Papistis, nonideo ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesias apud eos esse inficia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, sed tantum litigamus de vera &amp; legitima ecclesiae con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutione, &amp;c. i. e.</hi> When as we refuse absolutely to grant the Title of Church unto Papists, we do not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deny that there are chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches among them; but we strive for the true and lawful constitution of the church, which is required as well in the participation of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, as especially the Doctrine.</p>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:121294:55"/>
                     <p>Churches he grants to be, to remain under the Popes tyranny; but impiously pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faned, miserably afflicted and corrupted with pernicious er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: <hi>In quibus semisepultus latet Christus, obrutum Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium, profligata pietas, cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Dei ferè abolitus; in qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus danique omnia sic sunt conturbata, ut Babylonis po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius quam civitatis sanctae fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies apareat.</hi> Wherein Christ lieth buried, the Gospel over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed, Piety banished, and the Worship of God almost abolished: Lastly, where all things are so confused, that it appeareth rather to be <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> then to have so much as a shew of the holy City.</p>
                     <p>To the third, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> As <hi>Calvin</hi> before, so <hi>Junius</hi> is cited to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:121294:56"/>halfs. The full passage stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth thus in him: <hi>The church of</hi> Rome <hi>(as it hath that in it which belongs to the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a church) is a church:</hi> qua vero habet in se adna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum malum, quod Papalita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem dicimus, eo respectu ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesia non est: <hi>as it hath a disease, or evil growing in it, which we call Papacy, in that respect it is not a church.</hi> In this place he fitly compares the church to a body or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, capable both of health and sickness: the sincere and Catholick Profession he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembles to Health; the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, or Papal Hierarchy, and other corrupt Doctrines of the Church, he rightly and very significantly calleth <hi>a Disease or Sickness;</hi> a <hi>plague</hi>
                        <pb n="99" facs="tcp:121294:56"/>or <hi>canker,</hi> a <hi>consumption</hi> or <hi>poyson</hi> in this body: and then concludes, <hi>That the Roman Synagogue is a church, but a corrupt church: a church tain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with so strong a poyson, as unless it purge out the same, cunnot be saved: and still as more or less Papality is in it, the more weak or strong it groweth: and if God shall (which we earnestly desire he may) administer a strong an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidote, it may recover the health which once it had; but if the poyson still continue in it, it cannot chuse but at length all the vital spirits and passages of breath and life, which now it draweth in a fainting and languishing ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, will be utterly stifled and stopped.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:121294:57"/>
                     <p>To the fourth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iv."/> which is <hi>Fields,</hi> I need not answer at all: for I grant his Assertion <hi>in terminis;</hi> especially with his Addition in the same place, <hi>not a true church. The Romish Synagogue is truely a church, thut is, a company of men prosessing the Christian Faith: not a true church, that is, an Orthodox or right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving church, but very er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious and heretieal.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the fifth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="v."/> which is <hi>Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius,</hi> He (as <hi>Field,</hi> and the rest before) should have ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther been produced as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness on our side, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst us: for he saith in the very place alledged by the Adversary, That <hi>if we bring the Roman church to the touch, she will be cast for a meer coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit:
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:121294:57"/>she is as far from truth, as truth from falshood. Yet a church she is; but</hi> (as he there addeth) <hi>so corrupted and depraved, and with so great tyranny oppressed, that you can neither with a good conscience partake with her in holy things, nor safely dwell by her. She is</hi> (to use his si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude) <hi>like an adultercss wife, not divorced by her hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band; but yet not onely defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but openly convinced of whoredom.</hi> Such a woman, so long as her husband is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed not to sue out a Bill of Divorce against her, is a wife, but no true or loyall wife.</p>
                     <p>To the sixth, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vi."/> which is Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Crakenthorps,</hi> I answer: Though in my Copy, in the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:121294:58"/>title of his Treatise I finde the <hi>church of</hi> Rome a <hi>true vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible church,</hi> yet all that is proved in the Argument al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged above out of him, or in that whole Treatise, is but, That the Roman Synagogue is <hi>a church;</hi> to which the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward preaching of the Word, and administration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, is sufficient. But to prove her to be a <hi>true church</hi> he must have demonstrated the marks of a true church in her, which are <hi>pura verbi predicatio, &amp; legitima sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentorum administratio;</hi> pure preaching of the word, and right administration of the sacraments. These marks he proveth <hi>not</hi> to be in her most truly and solidly; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his meaning must needs
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:121294:58"/>be onely this, That she is <hi>tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a church, but not a true or right believing church:</hi> a church wherein there is <hi>pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sibility of salvation,</hi> not a <hi>true church</hi> wherein there is <hi>certainty.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To the seventh, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="vii."/> which is Doctor <hi>Halls</hi> Bishop of <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> I answer: That he, as Doctor <hi>Crakenthorp</hi> before, referreth <hi>true</hi> to <hi>visible,</hi> not to <hi>church;</hi> and his meaning is, That the Roman is a <hi>true visible,</hi> but not a <hi>true church.</hi> Fundamental <hi>truth,</hi> I grant, is like that <hi>Maronean Wine</hi> (as I said before) <hi>which if it be mixt with twenty times so much water, holds it strength:</hi> but the Romish Doctrine is rather like that Wine in the chalice given to Pope <hi>Victor,</hi>
                        <pb n="104" facs="tcp:121294:59"/>which was mingled with poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. As the earth and rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bish wherewith the Pagans overwhelmed the Sepulchre of Christ, was not the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre of Christ; and much less was the temple of impure <hi>Venus</hi> which they built over it, his sepulchre; yet his fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre was truly under it: So the Papacy is not the church, though under it the church be. And that this was the meaning of that most learned and judicious Bishop, appeares in his Reconciler, <hi>page</hi> 60. where he thus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preteth his owne meaning, <hi>viz.</hi>
                        <q>I say, that she is <hi>a true church,</hi> but I say withal that she is <hi>a false church: true</hi> in existence, but <hi>false</hi> in belief. <hi>Trueness</hi> of <hi>being,</hi> and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:121294:59"/>visibility, are no praise to her; yea, they are ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations to her falshood. And as a cheater is a true, though false, man; so we may &amp; must say, the church of <hi>Rome</hi> is a <hi>true,</hi> though <hi>false,</hi> church. Certainely there hath been a <hi>true</hi> error and mistaking of the sense, that is guilty of this quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel: And again, that face, that profession, those avowed principles which the church of <hi>Rome</hi> alloweth, are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to give it claim to a true outward visibility of a Christian Church; while those damnable inferences which it maketh from them are enough to feoffe it in the true style of Heresie and Antichristianism.</q>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:121294:60"/>
                     <p>As for the renowned Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conds of this Bishop, they rather purge him from any ill meaning, than justifie that speech of his. For by name the Bishop of <hi>Sarum</hi> writeth, that this Proposition of the Bishop of <hi>Exons,</hi> to wit, that the <hi>Roman church remains a true visible church, is an ill sounding Proposition in the ears of Protestants, especially such as are not throughly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with School distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions.</hi> For though men skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in Metaphysicks hold it for a Maxime, <hi>Ens verum &amp; bonum convertuntur;</hi> that which is true, is good: and that which is good, is true: yet with us he that shall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm such a one is a <hi>true</hi> chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian, a <hi>true</hi> Gentleman, a
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:121294:60"/>
                        <hi>true</hi> Scholar, or the like, is conceived not only to ascribe <hi>trueness</hi> of <hi>being</hi> to all these, but those due qualities, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisite actions, whereby they are made commendable, or praise-worthy in their several kindes. In this sense the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man church is not more a <hi>true Church</hi> in respect of Christ, or those due qualities or proper Actions which Christ requires, than an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant whore is a true and loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Wife to her Husband. I durst upon my Oath be one or your Compurgators, that you never intended to adorn that strumpet with the title of a <hi>trne Church</hi> in this mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus we see the Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for the <hi>truth</hi> of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:121294:61"/>man <hi>church</hi> are but few; and these neither direct, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press: whereas the contrary Testimonies are far more, and more express, and of more credit. Therefore if the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages on both sides are truly numbred, or indifferently weighed, we shall surely carry it. For if we adde to the Greek, and Affrican, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siatick, and Ethiopian, and Abyssen, and Indian, and Muscovite Churches, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in <hi>England, France,</hi> the <hi>Low-countreys,</hi> and <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many;</hi> we shall finde that the whole world in a maner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spireth in this truth, <hi>That the church of</hi> Rome <hi>is not the true church.</hi> As the Testimonies on this side are infinitely more in number, so much
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:121294:61"/>more direct and expresse. They that say the Roman is a <hi>true church,</hi> do but speak it <hi>lispingly,</hi> in <hi>some sense,</hi> and with <hi>divers restrictions and limitations:</hi> but those who deny it, and disprove it to be a <hi>true church,</hi> speak <hi>plainly and roundly, without any am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguity at all.</hi> In the Homily for Whit-sunday, page 213. We <hi>may well conclude accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rule of St.</hi> Austine, <hi>That the Bishop of</hi> Rome <hi>and their adherents, are not the true church: and if we com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the definition of the true church, with the church of</hi> Rome, <hi>not as it was in the beginning, but as it is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently; then shall we perceive the state thereof to be so far wide from the nature of the
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:121294:62"/>true church, as nothing can be more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Doctor <hi>Whitaker</hi> (that gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Taper of <hi>Cambridge</hi>) cont. 2. q. 6. cap. 1. propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this question in <hi>termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, An ecclesia Romana sit vera ecclesia Christi visibilis, i. e.</hi> Whether the Roman Church be a true visible church of Christ? thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termineth it: <hi>We say it is not onely not the onely catholick, but not at all catholick: not onely not catholick, to wit, universal, but we contend it is not a true church of Christ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And <hi>Willet</hi> in his second Controversie concerning the Church, quest. 4. page 115. undertaketh to prove this Conclusion <hi>terminis termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nantibus,</hi> as the Schooles
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:121294:62"/>speak, <hi>i. e.</hi> in concluding tearms, <hi>That the Roman is not a true visible church.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Lastly, as the Testimonies on our side are more direct and express, so they are much more to be credited then those which are brought for the adverse part: For one man that sealeth a Truth with his blood, is of more worth then ten who signed it onely with Ink: one Marryr pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponderateth ten Confessors. Now whereas those on the contrary opinion cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce one true Martyr who died for maintaining this As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sertion, That the Roman church is a <hi>true church,</hi> we can produce divers holy Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, as namely,
<note place="margin">Fox <hi>Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
                        </note> Master <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Thomas Osmond, Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:121294:63"/>Bamford, Nicholas Chamberlain, Robert Glover, Thomas Man,</hi> and others; who have sealed this Truth with their last Breath, and <hi>illustrated</hi> it <hi>by the fire of their Martyrdom, That the Popish Church is not the true church of Christ.</hi> These are now arrayed with <hi>long white robes;</hi> and God forbid that any true Professor of the Gos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel should go about to <hi>stain them with this foul aspersion,</hi> That they died like fools, and suffered for errour, or obstinacy, or uncharitably censuring of the church of <hi>Rome.</hi> I conclude therefore, That though the Romish Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue may be truely and rightly styled <hi>a church,</hi> both opposite (in opposition to
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:121294:63"/>Jews, Turks, Pagans, and Infidels, which are apparant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of the church) and positive) positively also in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of Gods right to her, and tolerating her, (though she deserve to be divorced) and his calling some to the knowledge of the Truth by the Word preached in her, though corruptly; and in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of her profession of such fundamental Truths as are absolutely requisite to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a church: yet that she cannot be called <hi>a true church,</hi> neither in the ordinary ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception of the word in the English tongue: nor <hi>in sensu Theologico,</hi> in the sense of all the reformed Divines, who have professedly handled the great Question between us,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:121294:64"/>and the church of <hi>Rome, de notis verae ecclesiae,</hi> of the notes of the true church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:121294:64"/>
                  <p>A SUCCINCT HISTORY OF THE Life and Death OF THE Learned and Famous Divine, <hi>DANIEL FEATLY</hi> Doctor in Divinity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nath. Brook,</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1660.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:121294:65"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:121294:65"/>
                  <head>A Succinct HISTORY OF THE Life and Death Of the Learned and famous Divine, <hi>Daniel Featley</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in Divinity.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentle Reader,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Must begin with a Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, both for thy <hi>Pity,</hi> and for thy <hi>Pardon.</hi> A friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly importunity (which seem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to have some tincture of tyranny) imposeth this task, and admitteth no excuse.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:121294:66"/>The guilt of my weakness and insufficiency is control<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the strength of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drawn from the due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye of Consanguinity; of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice to the dead, of bringing glory to God in an endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor to preserve
<note n="a" place="margin">Psal. 112 6.</note> the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in everlasting remember<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, with many more, which for brevity sake I purposely omit. I am therefore so divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in mine own thoughts, that even that alone might satisfie others, and be an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology for my silence. But necessity is laid upon me, and I <hi>must</hi> obey. Sighs abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at this unwelcome office of <hi>winding up in a sheet</hi> an Uncle so loving, a Friend so faithful, and an Instructer so Learned and Orthodox, are
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:121294:66"/>humble Orators, and beg thy <hi>pity:</hi> and my present absence from mine own study, and the sense of mine inabilities to answer expectation, sue for thy <hi>pardon.</hi> In hope of both I return thee a promise, That neither propinquity of blood, nor an uncharitable (although in the language of the world <hi>deserved</hi>) revenge, nor any thing else shall byass me to write a voluntary untruth: But (according to the Rule of the Great Orator) what I write, shall be not onely <hi>Testis temporum,</hi> but also <hi>Lux ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis.</hi> Be confident hereof, and read as followeth.</p>
                  <p>The first subject I shall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist upon, is the <hi>Quid nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> the Name of <hi>Featley:</hi> which indeed belonged not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:121294:67"/>to the Doctor; but was the issue of the ignorance and corruption of the times. His right name was <hi>Faireclough;</hi> and by that name he was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained both Deacon and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, as his Letters of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders witnessed. All the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Deeds, Evidences, and Conveyances of his Elder brother, his father, his grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, and the rest of his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestors, ran in the name of <hi>Faireclough;</hi> yea, and his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der brother (my dear Father) did constantly write his name <hi>John Faireclough,</hi> as I can justly witness. But even in the days of my good Father, the name (by the mistakes of people) varied and altered from <hi>Faireclough</hi> to <hi>Faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cley,</hi> then to <hi>Fateley,</hi> and at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:121294:67"/>length to <hi>Featley,</hi> which name he first owned in print of all our Family. He was extracted originally out of <hi>Lancashire,</hi> where many of the Family do to this day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the ancient and primitive name of <hi>Faircelough,</hi> and give the self same Coat of Arms with us, without the least distinction or alteration; which (if I had leisure and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to search) I doubt not but I should prove to be much more ancient then Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster <hi>Peacham</hi> in his Book of <hi>Heraldry</hi> would make it, who deriveth it but from <hi>Bosworth</hi> Field, in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh. The name at first arose from that <hi>fair Cliff</hi> where his Ancest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors long since were seated;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:121294:68"/>for in the Dialect of that County, as well as some o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, a <hi>Cliff</hi> was anciently written <hi>Clough;</hi> and so from their Seat the Family took denomination of <hi>Fairclough,</hi> retaining the ancient way of spelling the word. But of this enough.</p>
                  <p>My next subject must be the <hi>quid rei,</hi> or <hi>personae,</hi> the person himself. The Family of the <hi>Faire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>loughs</hi> in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times growing numer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, their Estate lessened by the increase of their Issue; for the Land was given by par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels to their children, and each Generation chipped and pared the ancient Demesnry. Amongst those many slips which sprung from the first Root, some kept their pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:121294:68"/>at home, but some were transplanted into one County, and some into an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: Those at home grew in their own native Soyl, but flourished not much, because they bore so fast. Those a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad betook themselves to several employments, and their fortunes were various. The good old Father of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Featley,</hi> was one of those whom Providence removed into another county, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in <hi>Oxfordshire.</hi> There in his youthful days he married Mistress <hi>Marian Thrift,</hi> and by her he had issue three sons, <hi>John, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam;</hi> and two daughters, <hi>Margaret</hi> and <hi>Anne. Daniel</hi> the second son, was born at <hi>Charlton</hi> upon <hi>Oatemoor,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:121294:69"/>being a studious and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous childe, he profited at School beyond expectation, insomuch as when he was but twelve years old, he gained no small credit and applause by the Latine and Greek ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses which he frequently, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, and elegantly composed. His father entertaining an employment in <hi>Oxford,</hi> gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an opportunity to prefer his forward son <hi>Daniel</hi> to be first a Scholar, and then Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low of <hi>Corpus Christi</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, when Doctor <hi>Reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> was President thereof. There he spent many years in his studies, and took his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Batchelor and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster of Arts, performing his Exercises to the Admiration of the University. When he
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:121294:69"/>proceeded Master, he was made <hi>Terrae-filius</hi> at the Act, and gained such honor, that his fame grew high in both the Universities. Then he wholly applied himself to the study of Divinity, and having laid a solid foundation in the positive part, he betook him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to the Fathers, Councils, School-men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His ad mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Disputations, his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Sermons, his grave, yet affable Demeanor, and his other rare Accomplishments made him so renowned, that Sir <hi>Thomas Edmonds</hi> being dispatched by King <hi>James</hi> to lye Leiger-Embassadour in <hi>France,</hi> he made choice of this Gentleman to travel with him as his chaplain. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand he obeyed, and spent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:121294:70"/>three years in <hi>France</hi> in the house of the Embassadour. During that time he became the Honor both of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Nation; insomuch as his many Conflicts with, and Conquests of the learned <hi>Sorbonists,</hi> in defence of the Protestants, and opposition to the Papists, caused even those his Adversaries to give him this Encomium, that he was <hi>Featlaeus acutissimas a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cerrimusque.</hi> Upon his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into <hi>England</hi> he repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his Colledge again; where having spent some time, he proceeded Batche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor of Divinity, and preached that elegant, solid, and smart Latine Sermon which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in his <hi>Clavis mystica;</hi> wherein among those seventy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:121294:70"/>Sermons, the Reader may finde also many English ones preached at <hi>Paris,</hi> and those likewise which he rehearsed both in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and at <hi>Pauls</hi> Cross. From <hi>Oxford</hi> he was invited by Mr. <hi>Ezekiel As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cot</hi> (one of his Pupils) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the Rectory of <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill</hi> in <hi>Cornwall,</hi> and leaving the University, he betook himself thither. But his great renown suffered not his Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to continue under a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shel; for <hi>George Abbot</hi> Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> sent for him thence, and perswaded him to be his Domestick Chaplain, and to leave <hi>North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill</hi> to accept of <hi>Lambeth</hi> Rectory, although the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues thereof exceeded not the other. To <hi>Lambeth</hi> he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:121294:71"/>went, where (after he had continued a while in the Archbishops house) his Lord prevailed with him to take his degree of Doctor in <hi>Oxford,</hi> that he might entertain the Archbishop of <hi>Spalato</hi> with an Academick Treatment. He yielded to the motion, and acquitted himself with so much honor, that the Doctor of the Chair thought himself affronted by his son <hi>Featleys</hi> acuteness of Learning, sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of Wit, solidity of Judgement, smart Answers, and undainted Courage. The grave Father being puzzelled by his ingenious Son, and in the face of both Universities, and the Flower of the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Nobility and Gentry, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides many foreiners, he made
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:121294:71"/>that a quarrel which his son <hi>Featley</hi> made but his defence: and it proved at length the Task of the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> to compose the difference. From <hi>Oxford</hi> he returned loaden with learned Honor to his Lord again, and <hi>Spalato</hi> was so pleased with his <hi>Oxford</hi> Junkets, that he not onely rendred thanks to <hi>Canterbury</hi> for his Chaplains gallant deportment, but also gratified Doctor <hi>Featley</hi> with a Fellowship, or Brothers<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>place in the <hi>Savoy,</hi> whereof he was then Master. Long die he continue a Menial ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the Archbishop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment: peradventure he was too good to rise, and too learned to be promoted, lest
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:121294:72"/>he should eclipse the glory of his Seniors. At length the discontents of the Court and City, because Doctor <hi>Feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi> was kept still behinde the Hangings, flew to the ears of the Archbishop, whereupon he shortly after gave him the Rectory of <hi>Alhallows Broad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>street:</hi> But by reason of the thickness of the <hi>London</hi> air, and the many inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies which he daily met with, upon many solicitations his Lord yielded to an exchange of <hi>Broad-street</hi> for <hi>Acton,</hi> which is six miles from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and in a pleasant and healthful scituation. About the year 1642. and about the forty and fourth year of his age, the Doctor married an ancient, grave Gentlewoman
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:121294:72"/>called Mistress <hi>Joyce Hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> the Relict of Mr. <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loway,</hi> and formerly the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict of Mr. <hi>Thompson</hi> (both Merchants of <hi>London</hi>) and daughter of one Mr. <hi>Kerwin,</hi> who lived in a handsom house of her own in <hi>Kennington</hi> in <hi>Lambeth</hi> Parish, and being a great Florist, nourished a Garden which administred a sweet and delicate delight: But this Marriage he for a time concealed, and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the domestick service of his Lord. In the year 1625. (that great year of the raging pestilence in <hi>London</hi>) the Archbishop remov'd with his whole family from <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> to <hi>Croydon,</hi> for fear of the infection; where it fell out on a day that Doctor
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:121294:73"/>
                     <hi>Featley</hi> found himself some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what indisposed in point of health, but endeavoured to shake it off. Howsoever the Bishop was soon acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with it, (for great men want not their whispering in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencers) and presently he commanded the Doctors speedy removal out of his house. Honor, and wealth, and age, and the Ministerial function, were too weak ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to perswade the Bishop to withstand the fear of sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness and death. The wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was rainy, the ways foul, the Doctor not well, yet all these signified nothing, nor prevailed so much with his Lord, as to allow him to stay either in the house or town, or to lend him a Coach for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:121294:73"/>his easier and safer journey. The Doctor took horse, and by the providence of a better Lord, rode safely (though in much anguish and grief) to his own house at <hi>Kenning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> where by the care and nursery of his skilful and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving wife, and a divine bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon the means, he soon recovered; for his distemper was but a Cold. Upon his recovery, he removed his Books and other goods from <hi>Lambeth</hi> Palace to his own house, and so deserted the service of his Lord. Here I might recollect his many dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes with several Jesuits, as <hi>Sweet, Fisher, Musket,</hi> and others, which being long since printed, I voluntarily pretermit, that I may not be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:121294:74"/>tedious. I might remember the frowns he received for Licensing a Book of Mr. <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons</hi> upon the <hi>Colosians,</hi> and how he acquitted himself be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>James,</hi> proving that those sheets which gave offence, were added to the Book after his <hi>Imprimatur,</hi> and so neither licensed, nor so much as seen by him. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon his Majesty receiving such satisfaction, and having heard of the fame of Doctor <hi>Featley</hi> for his acuteness in Disputations, he was graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously pleased to engage with the Doctor in a Scholastick Duel; whereof the Reader may have a full account in that printed Book which is called <hi>Cygneacantio.</hi> I might call to minde that Book of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:121294:74"/>his, called <hi>The Hand-maid to Devotion,</hi> that hath lived so many Impressions, and which he composed in that pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lential year, upon his return from <hi>Croydon:</hi> for he was so sensible of the general cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, that he laid by his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemick Divinity, and wholly devoted himself to the study and practice of Piety and Charity. I might also adde many more passages of his former life, most worthy to live to future ages, but that I study brevity, and indeed I want some helps, my memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being treacherous, and my remembrancers dead. I shall therefore hasten to the even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his life, wherein I shall be the more copious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, because some things
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:121294:75"/>remain very fresh in my me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, whereof I was an eye and an ear witness, and the rest I shall borrow from the mouthes of persons of a clear and untainted repute.</p>
                  <p>In the year 1642. (for far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther back I intend not to look) the Drums and Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets awaked our Nation, and the Riddle of the Parliament puzzelled the understandings of our learnedest Divines. Soldiers were raised <hi>for the King and Parliament,</hi> but how little they conduced to the honor, profit, or safety of the King, time and bad men discovered to the world. The soft and wanton peace of our nation was soon turned into rough and bloody Wars, <hi>Jusque datum sceleri:</hi> into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:121294:75"/>un-christian (or howsoever un-Protestant) rebellion and Insurrection against their lawful Prince: and a faction of Reformers so pretended to new inspirations, as if the private whispers of a fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick spirit had more and true Divinitie then the whole Church of <hi>England.</hi> The pretences were specious and prevalent; but the politick fraud, the (<hi>Anguis in herba,</hi> was carefully concealed. The <hi>King</hi> ('tis true) could not erre (for as yet they pretended to assert this Maxime of State:) but his <hi>evil counsellers</hi> might To save therefore and defend the Honour and Majesty of the <hi>King,</hi> his <hi>bad Councel</hi> must be removed, (they wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a true and faithful Glass
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:121294:76"/>to make them see <hi>themselves</hi>) and this must be done by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>distinguishing Weapons of Wars, and Engines of the greatest Hostility: not (oh by no means) to hurt the <hi>King;</hi> but onely to remove his <hi>evil Advisers.</hi> In brief, upon this very account <hi>Kenton</hi> Field was surfeited with blood: and shortly after that, the <hi>Thames</hi> at <hi>Brainford</hi> was coloured with the <hi>Red-coats,</hi> whose tin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture was as well a <hi>London stain,</hi> as an <hi>Edge-hill dy.</hi> Yet a fag end of these <hi>flesh-mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> (a rump of the City <hi>Butchers</hi>) who escaped <hi>dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping</hi> in the river, hastened to <hi>Acton</hi> where our <hi>Doctor</hi> was beneficed, and where my self then lived, and constantly preached. So soon as they
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:121294:76"/>came thither, to the <hi>Church</hi> they went: peradventure you may suppose they were zeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and good <hi>Christians.</hi> But be not deceived: they went not thither to <hi>pray,</hi> but to <hi>plunder;</hi> not for <hi>devotion,</hi> but <hi>desolation:</hi> to <hi>support</hi> it by <hi>destroying</hi> it; as they had lately fought to <hi>save</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> by their endeavors to <hi>slay</hi> him. First therefore they fell upon the <hi>Rails</hi> (perhaps taking them for <hi>Smithfield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens,</hi>) and broke them down and burned them. Had those <hi>Reformers</hi> been sacrificed in their own holy fire, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent sheep and lambs of Christ might have hoped to escape. Their next inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was for the Book of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer</hi> (for as they could
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:121294:77"/>not do their work <hi>without book,</hi> so they could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termit <hi>that book</hi> which smel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led so <hi>rank</hi> of <hi>piety</hi> and <hi>loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty:</hi>) but a young childe of mine, of his own accord, hid it from their discovery, and so saved it from their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. And truly if the <hi>Bible</hi> it self had been in their way, it is probable they would have condemned even <hi>that</hi> also to their devouring flames as heterodox to their new Opinions. Having burned the Rails, pulled down the Font, broken the Windows, searched for (but misled) the Book of Common-prayer, they grew weary of their vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lany for that time, and rested themselves a while. To the <hi>Communion-Table</hi> they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:121294:77"/>repaired, where they sate tipling so long, and so freely, (not onely the stron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gest Beer, but the strongest Waters also) that having drank too deep of those <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning spirits,</hi> they utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their minds in the Doctors seat, and in the very Pulpit did that which is worse. The whole Church at length was converted into a Lay-stall, insomuch as when the Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shioners assembled there a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the Religion of these Reformers <hi>turned their sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>machs,</hi> and <hi>stank</hi> in their no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strils. Yet all this in the judgement of the actors was piety, not profaneness: they had done too little. This con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned but the <hi>Steeple house,</hi> they had higher thoughts
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:121294:78"/>yet; they aimed at the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor.</hi> But for as much as he resided not at <hi>Acton,</hi> some of <hi>Urrey's</hi> soldiers resolved to keep house for him in his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and quartered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves at the Parsonage, where (not content with an hospita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble accommodation) they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to offer another sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to <hi>Vulcan.</hi> Two of his stables they burned to the ground, yea and his barn full of corn: the loss amounting to two hundred and eleven pounds. The zeal of these Incendiaries waxed so hot and furious, that nothing would satisfie them but fire and flames: and when the <hi>corn-fed</hi> bodies of themselves and their horses were <hi>pricked with their provender,</hi> they
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:121294:78"/>made themselves merry with their the <hi>frolick</hi> of their <hi>bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires.</hi> Yet was not their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice to the Doctor quenched with these flames: some of their tribe pursued him to <hi>Lambeth</hi> where he then resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and on the nineteenth day of <hi>February</hi> in the same year (being 1642.) even on the Lords-day, five of the new doctrined and discipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men of War rushed into the Church where he was then to preach, even in the time of divine Service, with Pistols and drawn Swords, not to defend, but to destroy the Gospel, and the Profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors thereof; and to murther one of the most learned and faithful Dispensers of the Word &amp; Sacraments. There
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:121294:79"/>they enquired diligently, and eagerly searched for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor: but Providence snatch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him <hi>as a brand out of the fire;</hi> for an honest Parishion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er stopped his journey when he was near the Church, and relating the news, disswaded him from running into such apparent danger. In the mean while those Janizaries growing impatient, and sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting the Doctor had met with some intelligence to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert him from preaching; in their fury they mortally wounded one of the Parishi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners even in the <hi>Church,</hi> and shot dead another, who but onely pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p'd over the church yard wall. So fierce and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous were these new-inspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Zealots, that neither the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:121294:79"/>sanctity of the day, nor the company of Christians as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled together for the Worship of the onely true God, nor the relative holiness of the Place, nor the sacred duty of Prayer, nor the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid crimes of Profaneness, Sacriledge, Murther of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians, and shedding the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood of the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd and sheep of Christ, nor any thing else could make them relent; but still they continued their resolutions to destroy the pious and harm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less Doctor. And when at length they found there was no hope of his coming, what they could not execute in deeds, they performed in words; for they <hi>breathed out slaughter</hi> and salvage murther
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:121294:80"/>against him, threatning to <hi>chap him as small as herbs to the pot,</hi> for suffering the Common-Prayer (which in the height of contempt they called <hi>Porridge</hi>) to be read in his Church. Surely if God had permitted them to be master of their design, such <hi>Porridge</hi> would have lost no <hi>savour</hi> by having so <hi>sweet</hi> and wholesom an <hi>herb chopped</hi> into them. Others of these mad <hi>brothers of the blade</hi> reported, that they would <hi>squeeze the Pope out of the Doctors belly.</hi> A subtile dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, a prodigious menace. He who was one of the most resolute, and most victorious Champions of the Reformed Protestant Religion, and of the smartest Scourges of the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:121294:80"/>Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was now accused for having <hi>a Pope in his belly:</hi> and the way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute him was by a martial <hi>squeeze,</hi> by strength of arms and dint of sword. <hi>O tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra! O mores! O calamitosam rerum divinarum &amp; humana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum faciem!</hi> O the sadness of those times, when accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <hi>covetousness</hi> painted over with a dissembled <hi>sanctity,</hi> seered and crusted the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of her paramours; and made them pursue their ungodly designs by calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious lyes, insurrections, trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, sacriledge, murther, and what not? The <hi>Papist</hi> was supposed the only <hi>enemy</hi> (but indeed the greatest <hi>abbetter</hi>) of the new Reformers of the Church: and wheresoever
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:121294:81"/>their black designs met with opposition, the bare imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Popery</hi> gave them a Commission to kill and plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Every one was then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused for a <hi>Papist</hi> that would not be a <hi>Sectary;</hi> and none were esteemed the <hi>Godly par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> but those alone who hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped to ruine the <hi>State,</hi> and destroy the <hi>Church.</hi> Now, alas, was that <hi>consummata in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foelicitas</hi> which <hi>Seneca</hi> speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of, <hi>Ubi iurpia non solum delectant, sed etiam placent:</hi> the <hi>abomination of desolation</hi> was come upon us, when all sorts of villanies were not onely acted with delight, but also justified as righteous. Well therefore might we mourn out that sad complaint of the same Philosopher, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sinit
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:121294:81"/>esse remedio locus, ubi quae fuerant vitia, mores fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt.</hi> Farewel Religion, when the <hi>old vices</hi> passed currant for <hi>new vertues;</hi> and the most piacular <hi>crimes</hi> were justified and applauded by the very <hi>Reformers.</hi> The intoxicated and infatuated people disclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Popery,</hi> to <hi>idolize</hi> some few of their <hi>Representatives:</hi> and pinning their <hi>implicite faith</hi> upon the sleeves of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sophisters, they took all for <hi>Orthodox</hi> which the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers voted for <hi>oracles.</hi> Thus did they insensibly lose at once not onely their reason, but also their Prince, their Loyalty, their Religion, their Propriety, and their Peace. But the more sober and ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious <hi>Protestants</hi> in the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:121294:82"/>mean while cousulted with true Divinity, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of well-guided Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences: and weighed not the present Distractions in the false scales of the cheating Zealots, but in <hi>the ballance of the Sanctuary.</hi> They found our Proprieties invaded, our Houses plundered, our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty confined, and (that which is dearest unto us) our pure <hi>Religion</hi> adulterated with impure schisms, and even <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of devils.</hi> Each day produced some new Opinion tending to the ruine both of Church and State; and those Enthusiasts who pretended to the guidance of a new and shining <hi>light,</hi> walked in the <hi>darkness</hi> of impiety and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableness, trampling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:121294:82"/>our Church as the Edo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites upon <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and crying, <hi>Raze it, raze it, even to the ground. Old</hi> and sound Truths were exploded, and justled out as <hi>obsolete,</hi> by a new-found divinity: and a <hi>Juncto</hi> of <hi>Novelists</hi> (some whereof peradventure had lately, and too justly been offended with un-warrantable innovations) made the world believe that they had heaven in a string, as the <hi>Trent</hi>-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers had the Holy Ghost in a Port-manteau. Kings were by them accounted useless; Allegiance superstitious; sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Oaths to our Sovereign Lord, rash and foolish Vows, rather to be penitently retra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, then conscientiously ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served; the Calling of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shops
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:121294:83"/>anti-christian; the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiastical Discipline, a rag of <hi>Rome:</hi> and all our sheaves must bow to that of <hi>New-England</hi> and <hi>Amsterdam.</hi> In the midst of these growing Heresies and Factions, our Doctor (with some others) preached up Loyalty and sound Divinity: yet not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the frowns of our <hi>Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees,</hi> and menaces of an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching <hi>Persecution.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon I frequently repaired to him, to consult and advise about the duty and safety of us both: for we clearly fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saw that although the <hi>black Cloud</hi> which hung over our heads was yet no broader than the palm of <hi>a mans hand;</hi> yet it might soon <hi>over-spread the whole heaven</hi> of our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:121294:83"/>Church. We apprehended that <hi>that gate</hi> which was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to the wrangling and infatuated Sectaries, would prove a <hi>trap-door</hi> to them that were sound and ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox: and that those who prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched <hi>up</hi> the Doctrine of our Church, would soon preach themselves <hi>out</hi> of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and Liberties. It was therefore his resolution that one of us should <hi>travel;</hi> for he was unwilling that our Mother the Church <hi>should be deprived of us both in one day;</hi> although I account my self one of the smallest and most inconsiderable Acomes, and as the least dust of the Ballance. To this purpose both <hi>he</hi> had received an invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation from the University of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:121294:84"/>
                     <hi>Leyden</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> to be <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of the Chair</hi> for Divini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and I from a very dear friend, to withdraw to Saint <hi>Christophers</hi> in the Western <hi>Indies,</hi> where I had the honor to be the first Preacher of the Gospel in the infancy of that Mother-Colony, in the year 1626. The choice was in him, who (concluding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self unfit to alter his climate, by reason of age, and other infirmities; and for other reasons which I purposely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit) resolved that I must pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide and fit my self for the Voyage. His counsel I fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and away I soon pac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; accompanied with my wife, children, servants, and what necessaries my slender fortune at that time afforded
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:121294:84"/>me. Sadly we parted; yet hoped that when the storm should cease we might meet again. But before my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture he committed the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Book, (which he had composed at the request of Mr. <hi>S. Birbeck,</hi> the Author of the Book Entituled, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian Evidences</hi>) as a sacred <hi>depositum;</hi> to my trust and care, reserving yet a Copy thereof to himself; and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that if either of us should survive the present distemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, it might one day appear in publick, for the edification of the Church. On <hi>June</hi> 24. 1643. I weighed Anchor at <hi>Tilbury-Hope,</hi> and thence proceeded in my Voyage, in a Ship sufficiently pestered with Brownists, Anabaptists,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:121294:85"/>Antinomians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In the mean while <hi>he</hi> stayed at home to <hi>fight with beasts at</hi> Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus, and defend the Truth. And indeed he had a fair op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity for it, being cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen a Member of the Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Divines, and wanting no courage either to preach the Truth in the Pulpit, or to assert and defend it in the Synod. In <hi>Lambeth</hi> Church (according to his custom) he so scourged the Times, that in <hi>July</hi> following three me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanick Brownists there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, exhibited against him no less than seven Articles to the <hi>Committee for Plundred Ministers,</hi> Mr. <hi>White</hi> (no great friend to orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines) having then the Chair. The Articles are extant in a
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:121294:85"/>Book Entituled, <hi>The gentle Lash,</hi> together with the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors Answers; whither for brevity sake, I refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. There he may find how earnestly the Doctor sued for a protection, that he might without peril of his <hi>life</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Committee: and he grounded his fears upon the jeers of his fanatick Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries continually scorning him; the musket of one <hi>Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood,</hi> a soldier, presented at him; the report of another soldier under the Command of Captain <hi>Andrews, That the Court of Guard at</hi> Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth <hi>should not be discharged until they had made an end of the Doctor;</hi> and, <hi>that they had a Warrant to plunder him.</hi> But how thick and dull
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:121294:86"/>(though <hi>long</hi> enough) were the ears of that Chair-man, and how impertinently he answered the Doctors re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest, by a pretence of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of what was alledged, the judicious Reader may be satisfied in the <hi>Gentle Lash.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And now appeared indeed the <hi>dubia crepuscula lucis,</hi> the <hi>twilight</hi> of the Doctors age: for he began his Answer to those Articles, with this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Complaint, <hi>Hoc uno die plus vixi quam oportuit;</hi> this is the first day in all my life, that I ever heard Articles read against me in any Court Ecclesiastical or Temporal, or Committee of Parlament. But he comforted himself with the example of Christ, the <hi>Prince of our salvation,</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:121294:86"/>who was <hi>consecrated through afflictions;</hi> and with that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology of St. <hi>Cyprian, Nec mihi ignominiosum est pati a meis quod passus est Christus; nec illis gloriosum facere quod fecit Judas, i.e.</hi> it is no disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor to me to suffer of my coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men what Christ endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; nor gain they any glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by doing like <hi>Judas.</hi> In brief, the Articles were so false, scandalous, undigested, and indeed foolish, that the Doctor was acquitted; and the compiler of them (one <hi>Ambrose Glover,</hi> alias, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews,</hi> a <hi>Botcher,</hi> who had spent a whole year in stitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them together) was dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missed with sufficient dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace. But these were not times for Sectaries to be foy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:121294:87"/>(especially at a Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee where the Chair-man was one of their stoutest Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions) and an Orthodox Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine go away with the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quest. The Articles were af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward taken into debate by four (too few for a Quorum) of the seventeen Members of that Committee, and right or wrong, they voted him out of his Living at <hi>Lambeth,</hi> Yet here they paused, and deferred the Report of their Order for above two months together. At length Master <hi>White,</hi> or some other for him, reported to the House of Commons their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings against the Doctor: where it was put to the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion, Whether he should be Sequestred, or not? and it
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:121294:87"/>was Resolved in the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
                  <p>Now the Doctor having his <hi>Quietus,</hi> he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self to be at liberty again to follow his Calling, and most weighty affairs: he therefore betook himself to his studies, both for the Service of God in the Pulpit, and for the dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of his Trust in the <hi>Assembly</hi> of Divines. But his Religion and his Loyalty were Crimes unpardonable: and his Vindication of the Truth in those erroneous times, betrayed him to the malice of new Adversaries, and their mischievous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivements. The <hi>Bishops</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voted down, and the <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy</hi> of our Church <hi>blown</hi> away with an <hi>unsavoury
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:121294:88"/>breath,</hi> every one's brain (<hi>mens</hi> &amp; <hi>womens</hi> of all sorts) hammered and projected a new Church-Government, (forgetting in the mean while that they had almost lost the very <hi>Church</hi> it self:) and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the many superfaetati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>that</hi> of the <hi>Presbytery</hi> appear'd most prevalent. The professors thereof in <hi>England</hi> learned their Lesson of their brethren in <hi>Scotland;</hi> whose first and greatest Lecture was the <hi>Solemn League and Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> it was hatched in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and sent to the As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembly of Divines in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> for their Concurrence. Being proposed in our <hi>Synod,</hi> the Doctor in a grave and learned Speech, and with so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and judicious Arguments,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:121294:88"/>so strongly opposed it; that those who wanted <hi>Learning</hi> to <hi>answer</hi> him, wanted not <hi>malice</hi> to <hi>ruine</hi> him. The Reader may be pleased to save me the labor of reciting the Speech, if <hi>he</hi> vouchsafe to peruse it in a Book Enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>Sacra Nemesis,</hi> Or, <hi>The Levites scourge.</hi> There he may finde not onely <hi>this</hi> Speech printed at large; but also <hi>others</hi> of great Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as also his <hi>Sixteen Reasons</hi> for <hi>Episcopal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment;</hi> and many other things well worthy his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>usal.</p>
                  <p>It seems the times would not bear <hi>sound Doctrine:</hi> it was therefore concluded by a factious party, that either the <hi>Covenant</hi> must be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press'd,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:121294:89"/>or the Doctors mouth must be stopped. Every <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctary</hi> was willing to help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the <hi>latter,</hi> in a seeming defence of the <hi>former:</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the zeal of some of them was not grounded so much upon their <hi>love</hi> to the <hi>Covenant,</hi> as upon their <hi>envying</hi> his <hi>abilities,</hi> and <hi>madness</hi> at his stout and reso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute defending the <hi>truth.</hi> At at last a Plot was laid by <hi>Schismaticks</hi> and <hi>Sectaries</hi> of several judgments (who all concurred (in the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign of silencing the Doctor) &amp; they built upon that Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Policy, <hi>Dolus, an virtus, quis in hoste requirit? Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems</hi> in wars are as lawful as <hi>battels.</hi> To this purpose, about the middle of <hi>Sept.</hi> in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:121294:89"/>year 1643, one <hi>Armiger Wardner</hi> (a proper Esquire, a despicable Felt-maker at that time in <hi>Southwark,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a <hi>Sutler</hi> in the Army at St. <hi>Albans)</hi> made his Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to the Doctor under pretence of friendship; &amp; pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately informed him, as from the <hi>Lord Primate of Armagh</hi> at <hi>Oxford</hi> (from whence he pretended he was newly come)
<q>That the King was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much offended at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the Assembly: and that he charged him upon his high displeasure, never more to meet with the Divines in <hi>Henry</hi> the sevenths Chappel.</q> The credulous Doctor intending no harm, suspected none: nor considered how strongly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:121294:90"/>and stoutly he had (but a fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night since) <hi>scourged</hi> the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> in that very <hi>Assembly;</hi> and that this therefore might be a Plot to affright him into a future <hi>complyance,</hi> or at least <hi>silence,</hi> in the <hi>Synode;</hi> or that it might be a <hi>snare</hi> to catch him, and to bring him into <hi>trouble. Evil be to him that evil thinketh;</hi> the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor thought none: but he seemed indeed a little <hi>unsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied,</hi> in that the Primate had not <hi>written</hi> unto him: but the cunning <hi>deceiver</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cused <hi>that</hi> by the danger of the times either to write, or carry intelligence of such concernment. The good Doctor was truly very much troubled at the <hi>contrary com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands</hi> of the <hi>King</hi> at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:121294:90"/>and the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Westminster:</hi> but the mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senger seemed to be <hi>grieved</hi> for him; and to <hi>contrive</hi> some means to quiet his thoughts. At length he told the Doctor, that a word of the <hi>Primat's</hi> mouth to the <hi>King</hi> would set all aright a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain: and that <hi>he</hi> was present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to return to <hi>Oxford;</hi> by whom if the Doctor would write a few lines to his <hi>Grace,</hi> acquainting him with some passages in the <hi>Assembly;</hi> and with his desire of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties leave to continue his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance <hi>there:</hi> he would not onely deliver the Letter with much fidelity, but also bring him an answer on tuesday following. Upon these fair shews of <hi>Armiger Waraners</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:121294:91"/>friendship, &amp; many promises of his faithfulness &amp; secrecy; the Doctor caused a kinsman of his to write what he dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>Armiger Wardner</hi> being in presence: and when he had finished, and read it to them both; the Doctor asked <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miger Wardners</hi> opinion, <hi>Whether he thought there could be any danger in send<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what was written?</hi> The <hi>Sutler</hi> pretended a <hi>confidence</hi> that there could be <hi>no danger</hi> in it: and therecupon the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor subscribed it with the two first letters of his name in Greek, one within ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, thus <figure/>; which afterward by the <hi>quiblet</hi> of a Member of Parliament was interpreted <hi>fidelity.</hi> He ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:121294:91"/>thus subscribed it, and folded it up after the manner of an ordinary written Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, (not like a <hi>Letter,</hi> nor yet <hi>sealing</hi> it) he delivered it to <hi>Armiger Wardner</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his <hi>Kinsman</hi> labored much by urgent Arguments to <hi>disswade</hi> him from it:) who soon departed, <hi>laughing in his sleeve.</hi> Towards <hi>South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark</hi> he marched: but at the <hi>Skonce</hi> by the way (as it seems the Plot had been laid) he was strictly examined, and searched for <hi>Letters.</hi> In his pocket was <hi>soon</hi> found this <hi>written Paper;</hi> and <hi>as soon</hi> it was confessed that he brought it from <hi>Doctor Feat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley,</hi> and was to carry it to the <hi>Primate of Armagh</hi> at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> The messenger was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:121294:92"/>(for fashions sake) clapped up for a <hi>Spie;</hi> but soon enlarged: and the <hi>Note</hi> or <hi>writing</hi> was speedily sent to the <hi>close Committee.</hi> They immediately perused it, and coppied it out: and then gave it again to the self same messenger to carry it to <hi>Oxford;</hi> hoping by these means to discover that <hi>intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence</hi> which (by their <hi>own</hi> encouragement) might af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward pass between the <hi>Primate</hi> and the <hi>Doctor.</hi> In conclusion, after some dayes had passed, and the thing was brought to maturity; the Doctor was sent for by the <hi>Close Committee;</hi> and charged as a <hi>Spie</hi> and <hi>Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligencer.</hi> He answered, that what he sent was but an open
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:121294:92"/>
                     <hi>note,</hi> and no formal or <hi>sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Letter:</hi> and if it had been a <hi>Letter,</hi> yet it contained no matter of <hi>intelligence</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the affairs of either <hi>War</hi> or <hi>State;</hi> but onely gave an account of some pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in the <hi>Assembly</hi> touching Religion; and <hi>that</hi> also, not to any <hi>enemy,</hi> but to a chosen <hi>member</hi> of the same <hi>Assembly;</hi> with friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counsel to the Primate to begge of his Majesty the Deanery of <hi>Westminster,</hi> then void, for his own ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessary <hi>support.</hi> Moreover, if it had been indeed a <hi>Letter</hi> (as it was not;) and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he had sent <hi>secret intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence;</hi> yea, and of matters of <hi>State;</hi> and all this to a known and professed <hi>enemy</hi>
                     <pb n="56" facs="tcp:121294:93"/>to the <hi>State;</hi> yet such a Letter could not in reason &amp; justice bring him within the compass of danger, because it was not a <hi>transgression of any known Law:</hi> for the Ordinance of Parliament forbidding correspondency by Letters to <hi>Oxford,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out leave of the Houses, or warrant from the Lord Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; was not then in <hi>being;</hi> but was made on <hi>Octob.</hi> 22th 1643: which was a full Moneth after this <hi>Note, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>script,</hi> or pretended <hi>Letter,</hi> was written. Again; if that note contained any dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>intelligence,</hi> or <hi>corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondency with any enemy:</hi> why did the Committee <hi>send</hi> it to <hi>Oxford;</hi> and not rather <hi>suppress</hi> it? Or why
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:121294:93"/>did not the Committee cause it to be afterward <hi>printed,</hi> that the world might know the <hi>crime</hi> of the Doctor? But the Doctors <hi>defence</hi> was not <hi>armour of proof</hi> against the malicious resolutions of his mortal Adversaries. The more reasons <hi>he</hi> urged, the more <hi>they</hi> were enraged: for what they were not able to answer by thestrength of <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> they howsoever could master by the strength of <hi>power.</hi> The <hi>Prolocutor</hi> was netled because the Doctor had written an <hi>Encomium</hi> of his special gift in praying not so much <hi>ex tempore</hi> as <hi>de tempore:</hi> and the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> were offended because he opposed the <hi>Covenant:</hi> and the Sectaries in general
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:121294:94"/>were highly displeased, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he both discovered and opposed their <hi>Schisms.</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the Committee (being of the <hi>discontented party</hi>) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solved to <hi>silence</hi> him: and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently he was voted both out of the <hi>Assembly,</hi> and out of his <hi>Estate</hi> and <hi>Liberty.</hi> On September 30<seg rend="sup">th</seg> a <hi>Warrant</hi> (mentioning no <hi>crime</hi>) was brought from the Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tee, to <hi>commit</hi> the poor Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor: and the Officer condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him to the Lord <hi>Peter's</hi> House in <hi>Aldersgate-street:</hi> before which he was so <hi>plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered,</hi> that he had no more money left him than one bare <hi>five shillings</hi> Piece of Gold; which he bestowed upon the Officer. So soon as he was <hi>laid up,</hi> those whose <hi>mouthes</hi>
                     <pb n="59" facs="tcp:121294:94"/>had long <hi>gaped</hi> and <hi>watered</hi> at his two <hi>Livings,</hi> and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly had been very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strumental to <hi>clap</hi> him <hi>up, skipped</hi> hastily into them: Mr. <hi>White</hi> of <hi>Dorchester</hi> into <hi>Lambeth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Philip Nye</hi> (this was <hi>that</hi> Nye, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) into <hi>Acton.</hi> Thus (oh thus) was the poor Doctor plundered, sequestred, imprisoned, and even quite lost to the world. Yet (as if malice had plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for <hi>eternity</hi>) they left him not <hi>thus:</hi> for whilest he was penn'd up in that noysom Prison, he yet <hi>preached</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly every Lords-day to his fellow-sufferers (for they were many, and persons of quality; and their sinne was <hi>Loyalty:</hi>) until at length <hi>Isaac Pennington,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:121294:95"/>Lord Major of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> stopped his mouth; and gave order that he should preach no more. Many sad moneths did he spend in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, wanting the sweet and pleasant <hi>air</hi> at <hi>Kennington,</hi> the comfortable Society of his <hi>Books,</hi> his just <hi>Revenue,</hi> a convenient <hi>accommodation,</hi> a well-ordered <hi>dyet,</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of his old and bosom <hi>friends;</hi> and indeed all things (except a <hi>good Conscience</hi>) which might qualifie the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terness of a tedious life. In the height of these his suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, it happened that a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist</hi> sent a bold <hi>challenge</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad into the world, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Antiquity, Unity, Universality, Succession, and perpetual Visibility</hi> of the <hi>true
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:121294:95"/>Church:</hi> which threw <hi>dirt</hi> in the <hi>face</hi> of the <hi>Protestant Church;</hi> and (as the Author thought) <hi>invincibly</hi> asserted the Tenets of the <hi>Romanists.</hi> The Parliament <hi>saw</hi> the <hi>chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge;</hi> but neither could <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer</hi> it themselves, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade the Reverend <hi>Synod,</hi> (wherein were yet left many persons of great <hi>learning,</hi> and much <hi>estimation:</hi>) but it was recommended to the <hi>Doctor;</hi> whom they knew to be well versed in the matters in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion. Had they first vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated him from the <hi>aspersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of the hackney <hi>Mercuries</hi> of the times, as <hi>Britannicus, Civicus</hi> &amp;c. and repaired his <hi>Losses,</hi> and restored his <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings,</hi> and enlarged his <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son,</hi> and sent him with honor
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:121294:96"/>to take his place again in the Assembly; they had given him a just and noble <hi>encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement</hi> to answer their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires. But he was a poor <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite</hi> under the <hi>Egyptian yoke;</hi> and must be content to abate the <hi>straw,</hi> yet make the <hi>brick.</hi> When no denial, or excuse, would satisfie; he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained that he wanted his <hi>Books:</hi> and without <hi>them</hi> he could not answer expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The House therefore vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>That he should have any of his own Bookes which he should require; provided that he should never have more than three of them at one time.</hi> By this Vote in the first place his <hi>Library</hi> was for a while preserved from the <hi>itching hands</hi> of Mr. <hi>White</hi>
                     <pb n="63" facs="tcp:121294:96"/>of <hi>Dorchester</hi> (who had got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten an Order, that <hi>he</hi> should have the Doctors <hi>Books,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til the Doctor could get back Mr. <hi>Whites,</hi> which some un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Command of Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> had seized at <hi>Dorche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster:</hi>) and the Doctor got a welcome <hi>imployment,</hi> which <hi>diverted</hi> the <hi>irksomness</hi> of his sad <hi>imprisonment.</hi> To work he went, and at length he fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished and published his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the Challenge, on <hi>August</hi> 1. 1644. in a Book Entituled, <hi>Roma Ruens.</hi> Nor may I here forget <hi>another Book</hi> which he had perfected and published the <hi>same year</hi> against the <hi>Anabaptists,</hi> and other <hi>Sectaries,</hi> called <hi>The Dippers dipt:</hi> both these Bookes being meanes to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crease
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:121294:97"/>his <hi>afflictions</hi> by the fury of so many <hi>Heretickes</hi> and <hi>Schismatickes;</hi> and few sound and solid <hi>Protestants</hi> left, to <hi>visit</hi> &amp; comfort him. Nor may I omit those foul and odious <hi>aspersions</hi> which the <hi>Sectaries</hi> (being enraged with madness at his <hi>Dippers dipt</hi>) and some others threw upon him, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Doctor</hi> Featley <hi>was turned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>apist.</hi> This abhorred <hi>imputation</hi> so terribly <hi>tormented</hi> him (much beyond his <hi>losses,</hi> and <hi>impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonment</hi>) that it compel'd him to <hi>vindicate</hi> himself in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner following.</p>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>Doctor</hi> Featley's <hi>Manifesto and Challenge.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <q>
                        <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                           <body>
                              <div type="manifesto">
                                 <p>VVHereas a false and scandalous
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:121294:97"/>report is <hi>bruited</hi> by the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi separatists</hi> and <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tists,</hi> and readily <hi>entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by diverse <hi>zealots</hi> of the <hi>new reformation, That I</hi> (who have preach'd so much against <hi>Popery</hi> heretofore) <hi>now in my old dayes</hi> (being ready to leave this world) <hi>have fallen away from my holy profession, and am in heart a Papist;</hi> there being found many <hi>Popish books</hi> in my Study: And because I have learned from the mouth of St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> that <hi>though other wrongs may be put up, and answered with silence, committing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge thereof to the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Judge,</hi> Injustissime judicato justissime judicatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro, i.e. <hi>to him who will
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:121294:98"/>judge righteously, although himself was unrighteously judged; yet that</hi> in suspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cione haereseos neminem o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet esse patientem. <hi>i. e. no man ought to be silent, when he is charged with he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resie:</hi> I have thought fit to make known to all whom it may concern, that being chosen <hi>Provost of Chelsey-Colledge,</hi> I have under the <hi>Broad Seal of England</hi> a Warrant to <hi>buy, have, and keep all manner of Popish Books:</hi> and that I never bought or kept any of them but to the end and purpose, the better to inform my self to refute them. And for my <hi>judgement</hi> and <hi>resoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> in point of <hi>Religion, I profess before God, and his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:121294:98"/>holy angels, and the whole world, that what I have here tofore preached, written, and printed against the errours, heresies, idolatry, and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold superstitions of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mish Church, I believe to be the truth of God; and that I am most ready and willing, if I be called thereunto, to sign and seal it with my blood</hi> And whereas I am certainly in ormed, that divers <hi>Lectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers</hi> and <hi>Preachers</hi> in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> and the Suburbs (who have <hi>entred upon the Labors</hi> of many worthy <hi>Divines,</hi> and <hi>reaped their harvests) do in their Pulpits,</hi> after a most insolent manner, insult upon them; demanding, <hi>Where are they now that dare stand up in defence of church-hierarchy,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:121294:99"/>or Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-prayer; or any way op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose or impugn the New in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Reformation; both in doctrine and discipline of the Church of</hi> England? I do here protest, That I do and will maintain, by <hi>dispu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,</hi> or <hi>writing,</hi> against a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them, these three <hi>Conclusions,</hi> viz.</p>
                                 <p>First, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="i."/> That the <hi>Articles of Religion,</hi> agreed upon in the year of our Lord 1562. by both Houses of <hi>Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> &amp; ratified by Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> need no <hi>altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> at all; but onely an <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox explication</hi> in some <hi>ambiguous phrases;</hi> and a <hi>vindication</hi> against <hi>false as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>persions.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="ii."/> That the <hi>Disci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline</hi>
                                    <pb n="69" facs="tcp:121294:99"/>of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> established by many <hi>Laws,</hi> and <hi>Acts</hi> of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that is, The Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by <hi>Bishops</hi> (removing all <hi>innovations</hi> and <hi>abuses</hi> in the <hi>execution</hi> thereof) is agreeable to <hi>Gods word;</hi> and a truely <hi>ancient</hi> and <hi>Aposto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical institution.</hi>
                                 </p>
                                 <p>Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="iii."/> That there ought to be a <hi>set-form</hi> of <hi>publick prayer:</hi> and that the Book of <hi>Common-prayer</hi> (the <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender</hi> being reformed in point of <hi>Apochryphal Saints</hi> and <hi>Chapters;</hi> some <hi>Rubricks</hi> explained; and some <hi>expres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions</hi> revised, and the whole <hi>correctedly</hi> printed; with all the <hi>Psalms, Chapters,</hi> and <hi>Allegations</hi> out of the Old and New <hi>Testament,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:121294:100"/>to the <hi>last Translation</hi>) is the <hi>most compleat, perfect, and exact Liturgy</hi> now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in the Christian world.</p>
                                 <closer>
                                    <signed>Daniel Featley.</signed>
                                 </closer>
                              </div>
                           </body>
                        </floatingText>
                     </q>
                     <p>After the Doctor had made publick this his <hi>Manifesto</hi> and <hi>Challenge</hi> (or howsoever owned it, as it is printed in <hi>The Gentle Lash</hi>) I could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hear that any <hi>confident Pen</hi> durst answer his <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge;</hi> or ever (otherwise than by some <hi>impudent lying Mercuries,</hi> or such <hi>scurrilous pamphlets</hi>) cast any further Aspersions of <hi>Popery</hi> upon him.</p>
                     <p>To draw near to a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion: Notwithstanding the great service which the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:121294:100"/>had done for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> at the request of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> by his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to that <hi>Popish Challenge</hi> in his <hi>Roma ruens;</hi> yet they suffered him to continue in <hi>Limbo,</hi> in his old <hi>prison.</hi> But when (after his long and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable durance) through the closeness and corruption of the <hi>air,</hi> the noisom <hi>stenches</hi> of the prison, his bad <hi>dyet</hi> and ill <hi>lodging,</hi> the want of <hi>exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cise,</hi> and many other <hi>incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniencies,</hi> he fell into a <hi>Dropsie,</hi> and other diseases: he became an humble Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner to the Parliament, that he might have leave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move to <hi>Chelsey-Colledge,</hi> where the <hi>air</hi> was <hi>fresh</hi> and <hi>wholesom:</hi> and his Physicians <hi>Certificate</hi> was annexed to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:121294:101"/>his <hi>Petition,</hi> declaring that he could not possibly <hi>live,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the benefit of better air. Full sixteen Weekes did his friends and servants bestow upon a daily and wearisome Attendance on the <hi>House,</hi> in pursuance of his request: for some <hi>Members</hi> would, but <hi>durst not</hi> move for him; some <hi>durst,</hi> but <hi>would not.</hi> His <hi>friends</hi> were <hi>fearful;</hi> but his <hi>enemies</hi> bold, and <hi>violent.</hi> At length (when his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saries were assured that his <hi>death</hi> approached; so that now there could be no fear of his further writing, or prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching either against the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> or any <hi>Anabaptisti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Tenets</hi>) they granted him an Order to <hi>remove</hi> to <hi>Chel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sey-Colledge</hi> for six weekes:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:121294:101"/>for (although they proved prophets, yet) they suspected that if he should be in any hope of recovery, he would fall again to his old game of Opposing the Heresies of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he times:) <hi>provided always,</hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat he should first give good <hi>Bayl</hi> for his <hi>return</hi> to prison at the six weeks end. By ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ue of this long looked-for Order he was <hi>removed</hi> to <hi>Chelsey-Colledge</hi> about the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ginning of <hi>March,</hi> in the year 1644, but neither <hi>physick,</hi> nor <hi>air,</hi> nor <hi>dyet,</hi> nor better <hi>lodging</hi> nor <hi>company,</hi> nor <hi>cordials,</hi> nor any thing else could <hi>remove</hi> his <hi>diseases,</hi> or give him hope of <hi>recovery.</hi> There he spun out a short time in much <hi>pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and holy exercises; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wearied with pains,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:121294:102"/>and worn out with <hi>afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> whereof none were so grievous to him, as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <hi>distractions</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> On the fourteenth day of the next moneth (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>April,</hi> in the year 1645.) the harbingers of death as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suring him of his near-ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching dissolution, he <hi>set his house in order,</hi> and made his last Will and Testament; which began thus:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>A Model of an in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ended Will to be Confirmed and Executed, if ever Peace return upon</hi> Israel.</head>
                     <p>
                        <q>FIrst for my <hi>Soul,</hi> I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to <hi>him</hi> whose due it is by a three-fold right; My <hi>Creator,</hi> who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fused it into me; My <hi>Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi>
                           <pb n="75" facs="tcp:121294:102"/>who freely ransomed it with his dearest blood; My <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> who assist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth me now in the greatest and latest assaults of temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. As for <hi>humane me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits,</hi> I renounce them all; accounting nothing in this kinde more truly honorable and meritorious, than the contempt of all me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ts: ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard, Sufficit ad meritum scire quod non sufficiunt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rita,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>The next day he made a Confession of his Faith to Doctor <hi>Loe,</hi> and the Dutch Embassador's Chaplains; say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moreover,
<q>
                           <hi>That the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which he had alwayes preached, and the Bookes
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:121294:103"/>which he had printed against-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptists, and other Sectaries, were agreeable to Gods word: and that he would S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>al the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>t Religion, as it was esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blished by the Acts of three pious Princes, with his blood. As for the Solemn League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> he said <hi>it was a damnable and execrable Oath▪ made pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posely to ensnare poor souls; and and full of malice and treason a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our Gracious Sovereign.</hi> As for the <hi>Church Government</hi> then controverted, he said, <hi>I dare boldly affirm, That the Hierarchy of Bishops is most a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Word of God, as being of Apostolical Institution; the taking away whereof is dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable: and that by consequence both the Presbyterian and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Governments are absurd, and erroneous; neither of them being ever heard of in the Church of God, till of late at</hi>
                           <pb n="77" facs="tcp:121294:103"/>Geneva: <hi>nor is there so much as any colour for them in Holy Writ. It is evident</hi> (said he) <hi>that as the Priests in the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were above the Levites; so in the New, the Apostles were above the disciples: and that the seven Angels of the seven Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the</hi> Apocalips, <hi>were se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Bishops: and that</hi> Polycar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus <hi>was Bishop of</hi> Smyrna, <hi>and</hi> Timotheus <hi>of</hi> Ephesus. <hi>And for the Laity, no pregnant proof can be produced that they ever med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with the Priests Function; or had any power to ordain Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters. And these things</hi> (said he) <hi>I intended to have published to the world, if God had spared me longer life: which I might tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row his goodness have enjoyed, had I not been unjustly impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soned.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                     <p>On the next day, being <hi>April</hi> 17. 1645. (which was
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:121294:104"/>the very last day of those <hi>six weeks</hi> which <hi>the tender mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies</hi> (that yet are <hi>cruel</hi>) of his enemies had alotted him for his continuance in <hi>Chelsey-Colledge</hi>) his <hi>spirit waxed faint;</hi> and (drawing neer to <hi>the gates of the grave</hi>) he prayed as followeth:</p>
                     <p>
                        <q>
                           <hi>Lord, strike through the reins of them that rise a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Church, and King; and let them be as chaff be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the wind, and as stubble before the fire. Let them be scattered as Partridges up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the mountains, and let the breath of the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume them: but upon our Gracious Sovereign, and his Posterity, let the Crown flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish. This</hi> (said he) <hi>is the hearty and earnest prayer of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:121294:104"/>a poor sick creature.</hi>
                        </q> With which words, and many hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Ejaculations, <hi>commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his soul into the hands of his faithful Creator,</hi> he <hi>fell asleep.</hi> So soon as he seemed to be <hi>departed,</hi> his Nephew, my dear Brother Mr. <hi>H. F.</hi> (not knowing what had happened) came thither to see him: but was enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained with the sad news of his Uncles <hi>decease.</hi> This struck him into such a grief, and astonishment; that (im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient of delay) he present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly caused a small <hi>dose</hi> of the Doctor's rare and precious <hi>Cordial Spirits</hi> to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stred unto him; which made him once more to open his eyes: and looking about him, and both <hi>seeing</hi> the tears of
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:121294:105"/>his mourning Kinsman, and <hi>hearing</hi> his passionate request to speak unto him; he said, <hi>Ah Cousin</hi> H. <hi>the poor Church of God is torn in pieces</hi> More he said not; but sweetly and gently groaned out his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried and fainting spirit; and resigned his Soul into the extended arms of his merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Redeemer.</p>
                     <p>And now (being above the further malice and blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirsty cruelty of his salvage enemies) provision was made for his honorable Interment: and in <hi>Lambeth</hi>-Chancel (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his desire) he was solemnly <hi>buried;</hi> a very great multitude of persons of <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor</hi> and <hi>quality</hi> attending the Funeral Rites; and Doctor <hi>Loc</hi> entertaining them with a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:121294:105"/>learned and pious <hi>Sermon,</hi> which was afterward printed: to which I refer the Reader for such further satisfaction concerning those rare Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complishments of the Decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, which <hi>modesty,</hi> and the feared suspicion of <hi>partiality,</hi> makes me forbear. All that I shall further write of him, shall be but a <hi>short</hi> Character of his <hi>Person</hi> and <hi>Graces.</hi> He was low of <hi>stature;</hi> yet of a lovely graceful <hi>countenance;</hi> and of a convenient strength and health of body. He was of a most sweet <hi>disposition,</hi> being <hi>affable</hi> and <hi>courteous</hi> to all; without the least com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixture of that sullen <hi>morosi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> which some men miss-take for <hi>gravity.</hi> He was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally free from all signs and
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:121294:106"/>shews both of <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</hi> onely when he disputed with <hi>Hereticks</hi> or <hi>Schisma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks</hi> in defence of the sacred <hi>Truth,</hi> his <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>dexterity</hi> made them unjustly suspect that he had been <hi>cholerick.</hi> He was such a <hi>Compendium</hi> of the learned <hi>Tongues,</hi> and all the Liberal <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences;</hi> that you would have thought him <hi>Learning it self</hi> bound up in a little and small Volume. He was most seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously and soundly <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>devout;</hi> freely <hi>charitable</hi> both in <hi>giving,</hi> and <hi>forgiving;</hi> and a faithful and true <hi>son of the Church of</hi> England. He was very <hi>temperate</hi> and <hi>sober</hi> in his <hi>dyet:</hi> yet such <hi>a lover of hospitality,</hi> that he requently and freely entertained stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:121294:106"/>at his plentiful (yet not prodigal) Table; seasoning his Discourse with ingenuous, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetious, and harmless mirth; yet never forgetting the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of a Divine. He dyed in the sixty fifth year of his age: yet truly if his unjust and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous <hi>imprisonment</hi> had not shuffled those <hi>diseases</hi> upon him which hastened his end, in humane probability he might have attained to the yeares of his aged Father, which were reckoned above an hundred.</p>
                     <p>Thus lived, and thus died the dearest to me of all my ablest friends; who very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten professed, That <hi>all his earthly care was for me, and mine.</hi> Yet as he was rendred unable to perform what he
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:121294:107"/>seriously intended me; so was I made uncapable of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended favors, by being then in mine <hi>exile.</hi> Little did I think that a Gentleman so healthful and temperate, was designed for so <hi>short</hi> a <hi>life,</hi> or (in some kinde) an <hi>untimely death.</hi> Oh my grief is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed by this imposed duty, and I am compelled to write <hi>in the anguish of my spirit.</hi> Yet some comfort I receive from the words of Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine, Vocantur ante tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus boni, ne diutius vexentur a noxiis: mali vero &amp; impii tolluntur, ne diutius bonos persequantur, i. e.</hi> The <hi>good</hi> are <hi>taken away,</hi> even before their time, that their persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may have a period: and the <hi>bad</hi> are <hi>hurried away,</hi> that
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:121294:107"/>they may persecute no more. My private and <hi>particular loss</hi> of him in this world, I can better <hi>bewayl</hi> than <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute:</hi> and truely how much our <hi>Church</hi> in <hi>general</hi> will miss him, nothing so much as bad times (I suppose) will dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. Peradventure one day <hi>that</hi> may be said of him, which that eloquent and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Orator of <hi>Oxford</hi> said of <hi>Zanchie, Beza, Reignolds, Junius,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cum nondum per aetatem aestimare potui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, (proh dolor!) amisimus. i. e.</hi> Whom we <hi>prized not</hi> whilest he <hi>lived,</hi> we <hi>lament</hi> now he is <hi>dead.</hi> In brief, he lived and dyed a <hi>Confessour,</hi> and a holy <hi>Martyr</hi> for <hi>God and the King:</hi> and he left behinde him such <hi>Monuments</hi>
                        <pb n="86" facs="tcp:121294:108"/>of both; that peradventure future Ages will alter the name in the Poet, to honor <hi>him</hi> with the verse,
<q>Marmora <hi>Featlaei</hi> vincunt monumenta libelli:</q>
                     </p>
                     <p>Reader, I have done; and thanking thee for thy pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and begging thy chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table pardon of what thou findest amiss; I rest</p>
                  </div>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Thine in all humility, and true Christianity,</hi> John Fairclough, <hi>vulgo</hi> Featley.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>London,</hi>
                        <date>July 13. 1660.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <pb facs="tcp:121294:108"/>
                  <head>Mistakes of the press correct as followeth, viz. In the Vindication, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>PAge 2. line Ult. read Hoc. p. 4. l. 13. r. Iliads. l. 18. r. alledged. p. 25. l. 5. r. Evangelij. l. 9. r. discern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. l. 17. r. sanam. p. 34. l. ult. r. saith. p. 35. l. 5. read treatises. p. 40. l. 20. r. talis. p. 41. l. 21. r. Harpalus. p. 46. l. 12. dele et. l. 13. r. aufert. p. 49. l. 20. foris. l. 22. r. beatitudinis. p. 54. l. 5. d. were. p. 62. l. 3. r. corpse. p. 66. l. 13. r. frusta. l. 22. r. reteins. l. 23. r. prints p. 100. l. 15. r. Zanchies.</p>
                  <p>In the Life and Death, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Page 6. l. 20. r. demeasne. p. 12. l. 17. r. undaunted. p. 14. l. 9 and l. 16. r. Breadstreet. l. 20. r. 1624. p. 21. l. 8. r. truer. p. 24. l. 18. r. missed. p. 30. l. 2. r. chop. l. 9. r. masters. p. 42. l. 10. r. dubiae.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:121294:109"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Books to be sold by</hi> Nath. Brook <hi>at the</hi> Angel <hi>in</hi> Cornhil.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. THe Accomplisht Cook, the Myste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the whole Art of Cookery revealed in a more easie and perfect Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod then hath been publisht in any Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage: expert and ready ways for the dressing of Flesh, Fowl, and Fish, the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of Pastes, the best directions for all manner of Kickshaws, and the most poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Sauces, with the terms of Carving and Sewing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Robert May,</hi> in the time of his attendance on several persons of Honor.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Character of <hi>Italy,</hi> or the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Anatomized by an English Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. The Character of <hi>Spain,</hi> or an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomy of their Virtues and Vices.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Christian Reformation:</hi> being an earnest Perswasion to the speedy practice of it, proposed to all. By <hi>Richard Parr,</hi> M. A. Pastor of <hi>Camorwel</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi> A piece fit to be known.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>